<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second letter to ABCDEF, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09993</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">69648909</idno>
  <idno type="VID">185067</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240886317</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2284A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183666</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">69648909</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09993)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 185067)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2885:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second letter to ABCDEF, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:185067:1"/>
            <head>A SECOND LETTER to <hi>ABCDEF,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THO, <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> Information is but thrown away, where there is wanting ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ingenuity to own Conviction, or Coolness to receive it; yet since your <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary</hi> has obliged me with notice of your expecting to hear further from me, I shall not decline the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Publick, whether I expose your way of writing, or my own: And since to me you seem pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess'd with a Warmth against the present Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I shall endeavour, if not to abate the heat of the distemper, yet to prevent its being catching.</p>
            <p>You must pardon my Fears, since you give grounds for 'em, that 'tis very near turning to the Frenzy of downright <hi>Toryism;</hi> which, if it be a relapse in any who had labour'd with that disease, but grew sober upon the Revolution; must needs become incurable. But I hope in most of you it may be check'd, upon discovery of the first Symptoms; and that you your selves will not believe the freedom you take with dead <hi>Tories,</hi> a greater evidence of your being out of all danger of that disease, than there are proofs of it, in your strict friendship with the living, and uniting in the same methods,<note place="margin">Hist. p. 46.</note> not only for <hi>clogging the Wheels</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:185067:2"/>of this Government, which you threaten; but for contributing to its subversion.</p>
            <p>This is no more than must be expected from <hi>Tories,</hi> as such: If Strangers cannot <hi>comprehend the nature of our Government,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Confutat. p. 31.</note> how the <hi>Monarchy</hi> should be <hi>heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi> and yet the Line of Succession not <hi>unalterable;</hi> 'tis certain a <hi>Tory</hi> has such an invincible Prejudice against this No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>n, that nothing can beat into his Noddle, what overthrows the <hi>Divine Right,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> of a Papist or Tyrant, whom the chance of Birth had placed next to the Throne. And when you talk of a King's having Power <hi>flowing from the People,</hi> they will tell you 'tis mere <hi>Blasphemy,</hi> and that <hi>Fortescue,</hi> whom you cite for it, was but an Advocate for an Usurper.</p>
            <p>Should a <hi>Tory</hi> rise from the dead, and inform his Brethren, to what vain Idols they had sacrificed, with their Prostitutions of all Rights, Sacred as well as Civil; 'twould be likely to have no greater effect upon them, than the Admonitions of <hi>Moses</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> had upon the obdurate <hi>Jews.</hi> But what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biass'd person can believe them to be in their right Wits, who not only expect the defence of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in all events, but their <hi>Free Government,</hi> under which they disguise their projected Scheme of a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,</hi> from a <hi>Coalition</hi> of <hi>Tories,</hi> with these <hi>free-spirited Gentlemen? Toryism</hi> is such a Taint, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a severer state of Purgation, than the most ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid Philosopher ever prescrib'd for subduing corrupt Nature: And tho the Venom seems to sleep, while the Party are under some mortifications, yet like a lurking Plague it insensibly spreads its Infection: One would think a little remembrance of its Ravages in the late Reigns, might be sufficient Antidote against
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:185067:2"/>its Contagion: they who shall go about to cover those <hi>livid Spots</hi> which many of 'em still carry about 'em, must needs be thought to have their Brains seiz'd with that <hi>Plague;</hi> and with the accursed desire of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating it to the sound.</p>
            <p>What else can one think of them, who when the Sincerity of some Promoters of their Project is que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion'd, say, without any exception of those who had been <hi>engaged</hi> against the Interest of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey,<note place="margin">Milit. ref. p. 10.</note>
               <hi>Charity commands us to hope the best:</hi> Yet will give no grains of allowance to others, who by their suffering for adhering to the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> had given full proofs of their Sincerity: but such of them as <hi>openly oppose</hi> a Chimerical <hi>Model</hi> of a <hi>Militia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 7.</note> must pass for <hi>Apostate Whigs.</hi> 'Tis certain that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever would sacrifice the Constitution of this Monarchy, or the only visible means of preserving it, to the interest of their Spleen or Party, must be <hi>Tories,</hi> whatever denomination they assume: They can now hope for no success against the present Settlement of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> but in disguise, and with the help of <hi>false Disciples,</hi> who may betray 'em with a Kiss.</p>
            <p>If these are to be distinguished from <hi>Tories,</hi> at least it must be agreed that they are far from being opposite to 'em, who maintain, That if <hi>Whigs be the only Persons intrusted, the Tories would justly continue still disaffected;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Milit. ref. p. 54.</note> as if their disaffection were so far from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving the pain of loss, that it ought to be a recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation to <hi>Trust.</hi> However I must own you very politickly make way for your own admissions, by the complying Rule which you deliver,<note place="margin">Ib.</note> That <hi>such as are not admitted to Confidence and Preferment, are most of 'em offended [upon no other score];</hi> according to which,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:185067:3"/>the professed zeal of any of you for a Government of your own, or rather Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi>'s Modelling,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> 1<seg rend="sup">st</seg> Letter shewing their Notions taken from <hi>H</hi>'s <hi>Ocea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na. Argument</hi> p. 15.</note> or of your new Friends, for <hi>King James;</hi> may be thought only in order to necessitate the Government to prefer the most clamorous, to stop their Mouths; and seems to point out the way of making you as bold <hi>Conspirators against your Country,</hi> as you repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent your old Friends, whom you charge with <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stacy:</hi> when the true ground of this black imputation is their not joining with the <hi>Tories;</hi> While, with the mask of Commonwealths-men, they undermine that Government which has wounded <hi>Toryism,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the fifth Rib; but as 'twas just expiring, their new Friends, by an unmerciful pity, gave life to the destruction of Mankind: which, without his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty</hi>'s glorious interposition, would not have left so much as the hopes of Civil Liberty, or freedom to profess the truly <hi>Reformed Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In such a state, some of them who hector and threaten a patient administration, would have been very silent and <hi>Passive;</hi> and others could not for shame vent any murmurs, against what they had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged and incited, by their <hi>slavish doctrines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Against which, they who have signalized them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves by an hazardous War, in times of the greatest danger, cannot but wonder at their assurance, who set up for Leaders in this noble Cause; and yet, like those who <hi>perished in the gainsaying of Corah,</hi> falsly represent their <hi>Great Deliverer</hi> from <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, as <hi>making himself altogether a Prince,</hi> or Abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute over 'em.</p>
            <p>When they who are so far from shewing any Scars in their Countries quarrel; that they were never heard of for <hi>Champions</hi> till that War was over, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:185067:3"/>nothing left 'em to Fight with but their own shadows, charge old Soldiers with <hi>Desertion</hi> and <hi>Apostacy,</hi> which is appropriated to Religion; 'tis natural to enquire from whence 'tis that they take to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves such an Authority of Stigmatizing whom they please: if 'tis not from their sufferings in the Cause, is it from the advantage of Education, or that su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior Nature which they have over the rest of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, which can comprehend all <hi>Mysteries,</hi> not only of State, but of Religion?</p>
            <p>If any of 'em were originally <hi>Papists,</hi> or <hi>Tories,</hi> the world will, doubtless, require other marks of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version, than advancing Reason into God's Throne, by representing Divine <hi>Mysteries</hi> as no more <hi>above</hi> Reason than <hi>contrary</hi> to it; or shaking the Throne of that Prince whom God has made the Instrument of our <hi>Deliverance,</hi> from <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Tyranny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatever are the Principles of these free Censu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of those who can't come up to their height; 'tis certain, that the load they lay upon the present Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration, is made up of matter, either wholly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious, or aggravated with much ill nature, and groundless suppositions.</p>
            <p>'Tis part of their unhappiness, that like Mr. <hi>Hobbs,</hi> whose Notions some of them ha before they could rightly distinguish; they judge of all Mankind by themselves; and think they are left to their own ways, without any restraint from Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Grace, or Providence: this I cannot but appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend to be the main foundation of the Politicks you, Gentlemen, advance; therefore 'tis that you tell us, you <hi>have not only your own Experience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. to the Hist.</note>
               <hi>but the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of all times to prove, that men in the same Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances will do the same things, call them by what names of distinction you please.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:185067:4"/>
            <p>What is this but that <hi>Whigs,</hi> even the virtuous Authors of that Remark, would be as arrant <hi>Tories</hi> as any were in the Reigns you Censure; if they had the same opportunities? And as this is said in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to our present Government; That <hi>King William,</hi> who both here, and in <hi>Holland,</hi> has given de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrations of his inflexible resolution to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Rights of those Nations over which he presides; if he had the like Power in his bands with our former Kings, would make the like use of it? When his whole Life is a confutation of that mean thought of human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which no honest mind could be guilty of. And if you could have one cool thought, you would find, that every Reign which you instance in, is a disproof of your Notion, and makes it evident. That under good Princes their Subjects have been happy, tho there was Force more than enough to have made them otherwise; as <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> whose Reign you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound as an Example, undoubtedly had, upon her disappointing the <hi>Spanish Invasion:</hi> And the Miseries which this Nation has endured, under any Kings or Queens, have been owing more to the Tempers of their <hi>Princes,</hi> and the Malignity of the <hi>Tories</hi> and their Predecessors, who have delighted in publick Calamities; than to those <hi>Mercenary Forces</hi> of which you pretend to give the History; but depart from it as much as the most injudicious Pulpiteer does from his Text.</p>
            <p>But whatever be the inclination of the <hi>Prince,</hi> or posture of Affairs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pref.</hi> A Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is a mere piece of Clockwork.</note> such State-<hi>Engineers,</hi> if we may believe 'em, have an Art to make all Governments move as regularly as any <hi>Piece of Clockwork;</hi> which having such Springs and <hi>Wheels,</hi> must act after such
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:185067:4"/>
               <hi>a manner; and therefore the Art is to constitute it so, that it must move to the Publick Advantage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One would think 'twere very difficult, whatever Climate men were under, how barbarous and unci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilized soever; yet to contrive a <hi>Machine of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> that should force all to act for the <hi>Publick Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You, before whose Understandings Sacred My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries vanish to nothing, are resolv'd that this shall not be kept in the dark; but for the full enlightning the Age, teach us,<note place="margin">Pref. to the Hist.</note>
               <hi>That as every man will act for his own Interest; all wise Governments are founded upon that Principle: So that this whole Mystery is only to make the Interest of the Governors and Governed the same.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To set your Notion about this in a true light; 'twill be requisite to lay together the different ways of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining your selves, upon this your great <hi>Arcanum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Preface to the History.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Argument, Page</hi> 4.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <q>In an <hi>Absolute Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> where the whole Power is in one man, his Interest will be only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded. In an <hi>Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy</hi> the Interest of a few; and in a <hi>Free Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> the Interest of every one: This would be the Case of <hi>England,</hi> if some Abuses, that have lately crept into our Constitution, were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:185067:5"/>The Freedom of this Kingdom de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the Peoples chusing the <hi>House of Commons,</hi> who are a part of the <hi>Legislative,</hi> and have the sole power of giving Money: Were this a <hi>true Representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and free from <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Force,</hi> or <hi>private Bribery,</hi> nothing could pass there, but what they thought was for the publick Advantage.</q>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:185067:4"/>
                        <q>Our Constitution de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon a <hi>due bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance</hi> between <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons;</hi> and that <hi>Ballance</hi> depending upon their mutual oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions and necessities they have of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; if this Cement be once broke, there is an actual <hi>dissolution of the Government.</hi> Now this <hi>Ballance</hi> can never be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:185067:5"/>preserv'd, but by an union of the <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Artificial Strengh</hi> of the Kingdom: That is, by making the <hi>Militia</hi> to consist of the same Persons <hi>as have the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty:</hi> or otherwise the Government is violent, and against Nature, and cannot possibly conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue; but the <hi>Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> must either break the <hi>Army,</hi> or the <hi>Army will destroy the Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> For it is univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally true, that where the Militia is, there is or will be the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a short time.</q>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>I would gladly know whether, though you seem to allow the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> to be part of the <hi>Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,</hi> according to your avowed Principle, to make this a <hi>Free Government</hi> (which you know it can't be till the <hi>Sword is in the hands of the People</hi>) and to have the <hi>Interest of the Governors and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned the same.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Militia Reform'd,</hi> p. 22. Where-ever the Sword is in the hands of the People, 'tis a Free Government, be it of One, or Many; and on the contrary, all Tyrannies are sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by Mercenaties.</note> 1. The <hi>Governors</hi> ought not to be such, as the <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned</hi> shall from time to time, in short Rotations, chuse from among themselves? 2. Whether the Stations both of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Lords,</hi> would not be at the pleasure of the People,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:185067:5"/>in whose hands you would have the Sword to be? and 3. Whether, to follow your own thoughts of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, they would not, as soon as they were possess'd of this power, make themselves that <hi>free state</hi> which you so openly contend for? The great Things <hi>King William</hi> had done for the Nation, and the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gratitude all of you, that are <hi>Englishmen,</hi> and <hi>Protestants,</hi> lie under; nay, which wise Papists thankfully acknowledge, will nothing to them, who in the same breath that they condemn those who <hi>Attribute all publick Miscarriages to the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Mankind,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prof.</hi> Most men having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digested Ideas of the Nature of it, attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> own this to be so Universal, that <hi>all men will do the same Things in the same Circumstances:</hi> that is, under the same Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Since, therefore, you give so true a Character of your selves, at least, you sufficiently warn the Government against trusting you with Power; and give Reputation to the prudent disposal and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Offices; which, according to your own Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, all <hi>Kings</hi> ought to be careful of, as they would preserve their Crowns: nor is that to be look'd on as a <hi>Bribe,</hi> which is but a further En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to Duty, or Reward for adhering to it.</p>
            <p>Indeed it has been found by sad Experience, that the giving Offices to Men by Principle, or Combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, against the Government, was but a lending Forces to the Enemy: and such men were Bribed so much higher, by their expectations upon a change; that their Offices rarely gained a Vote to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick: but, as these men would Sacrifice their Offices to destroy it, and thereby make way for their greater hopes; no Offices could corrupt true Patriots; nor can they be bestowed to an ill purpose, by a good
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:185067:6"/>Prince. To imagine, that your Notions of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Censures of the Powers that are over us, are any way applicable to the present Times, seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral invidious particulars must be unwarrantably sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed: As, 1. That the last Elections to Parliament, during His Majesty's Absence, were not free from External force: 2. That His Majesty, and the Court, have an Interest separate from that of the Publick: 3. That if there were private Bribery, it lay chiefly on the side of the Court. 4. That the Majority of the persons chosen, are capable of being Bribed against their Country, if it could be thought that His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty can have, or countenance any aims, contrary to the whole tendency of his Glorious Life.</p>
            <p>Indeed 'tis well known who they are, that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly would make King <hi>William</hi> as had as the worst of his Predecessors, by their Notions of Mankind, without restriction; but by their broad insinuations, and gross distortions of the Actions of a Prince, whom all Enemies, but such as would be thought <hi>Englishmen,</hi> speak of with greater Decency,<note place="margin">Dean <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi>'s Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression.</note> and that <hi>Euphemeia,</hi> with which some Gentlemen are but little acquainted. Their finest Expressions toward His Majesty, as they are accompanied, are no lefs mockery than theirs; who after they had Crown'd our Saviour with Thorns, in prophane derision, cri'd, <hi>Hail King of the Jews.</hi> And as 'tis their business to make Monarchy odious, 'tis no less to make Crowns so Thorny, that no Prince should be willing to wear one: which doubtless would come to pass here, if Princes could think such Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons a true Representative of the <hi>English</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>'Tis no great Mystery, Gentlemen, to whom you impute all the disappointments which we have had, from the Subtilty of Enemies, Treachery of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:185067:6"/>Friends, or numerous Accidents unforeseen: In your <hi>Argument,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P.19.</note> speaking of a Misapplication of our <hi>Naval</hi> Force for Eight years, you say in the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Number; <q>which unriddles a Mystery I did not understand before; though I never was so foolish as to believe all the Errors of that kind were the effects of Chance or Ignorance; or that losing so many opportunities of destroying the <hi>French</hi> Fleet, <hi>had not some extraordinary, though occult cause;</hi>
               </q> which you repeat in your History with little Variation,<note place="margin">P.23.</note> saying, <q>Though a great part of it may be Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Negligence, Ignorance, or Treachery of Inferior Officers; yet it could not so univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally happen through the whole Course of the War, and unpunished too, notwithstanding the Clamours of the Merchants, and repeated complaints in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>unless the Cause had laid deeper:</hi> What that is, I shall not presume to Enquire; but I am sure there has been a very ill Argument drawn from it, <hi>viz. That a Fleet is no security to us.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly, without any deep diving into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of your Reflection, the whole Scope of your Discourses in Print, and Coffee-Houses shew an insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation, as if the Navy has been render'd useless through the design of him, or them, who intended to set up a <hi>Standing Army.</hi> To know whether King <hi>William</hi> is concern'd in this Reflection, 'tis but turning to what you say towards this matter, as the <hi>Prince of Orange:</hi> speaking of the inducements men had to turn against King <hi>James,</hi> you say;<note place="margin">Hist. p.19.</note>
               <q>
                  <hi>By</hi> Which means they all united against him, and invited the <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> to assist them; which invitation he accepted, and Landed at <hi>Torbay,</hi> the 5th of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 1688. publishing a Declaration, which set
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:185067:7"/>forth all the Oppressions of the last Reign, [but the keeping up a <hi>Standing Army</hi>]; declared for a free Parliament, in which things were to be so setled, that there should be no danger of falling again in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Slavery, and promis'd to send back all his Forces as soon as this was done.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here, [but the keeping up a <hi>Standing Army</hi>] is put with particular marks of distinction, as mightily to be observ'd; when 'tis well known, that if that was a mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Omission, 'tis to be imputed to <hi>Major Wildman,</hi> and other <hi>Englishmen,</hi> whom you have in esteem, and who either penn'd or advised that Declaration; nor is this particular, that I remember, mentioned in a larger <hi>Manifesto,</hi> published by <hi>Major Wildman</hi> himself: nor indeed could have been urged with so much grounds as the other notorious violations of the Constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the Army having been rais'd in the defence of the then Government, against an Invasion by the <hi>Duke of Monmouth:</hi> which was very formidable, though he Landed with no more than 70 odd men: and was afterwards kept up in fear of the much greater power of His <hi>present Majesty,</hi> when but <hi>Prince of Orange.</hi> But here's too plain an insinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as if he broke his promise contained in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, in not sending back all his Foreign Forces, as soon as a free Parliament had been holden, <hi>and things so setled by that Parliament, that there should be no danger of falling again into slavery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, according to your Argument, as 'tis a state of Peace,<note place="margin">Letter from the Author of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. p. 4.</note> as soon as Terms are agreed on, and Signed, to your pleasant definition of <hi>Peace,</hi> there <hi>is a Cessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Exercise of the use of Arms;</hi> which may reach no further than a short truce, or only a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continuance
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:185067:7"/>of the Disciplining of Soldier, between Exercise and Exercise; so, as soon as the Bill of Rights was pass'd into an Act of Parliament, His Majesty was obliged to have sent back all his <hi>Foreign Forces:</hi> which if he had done, the Bill of Rights and been very insignificant; nor was the Militia of <hi>England</hi> likely so soon to have reduced a <hi>Scotch</hi> Regiment in actual Rebellion, as Collonel <hi>Eppingham</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Dutch</hi> Dragoons did.</p>
            <p>But,<note place="margin">Hist. p. 38.</note> Gentlemen, in whatever sense you took His Majesty's Declaration,<note place="margin">It was in that sense I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration.</note> had you not run it over with your usual heat and inconsideration, you would have send the Forces back, <hi>as soon as the state of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will admit of it.</hi> But certainly the restless Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of such persons as you well know, with the probability of the continuance of a Plot, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne the King, if not to <hi>murder</hi> him; and the grounds to believe that those Regiments which have been form'd in <hi>Lancashire,,</hi> and elsewhere, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of our Religion, and Liberties, are not bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; may occasion a consideration, whether the <hi>State of the Nation</hi> will <hi>yet admit</hi> of sending back the very few that remain of His Majesty's Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Forces.</p>
            <p>The manifest conviction of the unfairness of your insinuation, as if His Majesty had purposely omitted declaring against a <hi>Standing Army,</hi> because of his intention to keep one, and that contrary to his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration; may supersede, the considering many of your like perversions: To which that of the Poet is applicable:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Aut famam sequere, aut convernientia finge.</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:185067:8"/>
            <p>Which I may render,</p>
            <q>
               <hi>If you slight truth, feign what may be believ'd.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>'Twere to no purpose here to rake into all the filth of your <hi>Augoean</hi> Stable, 'tis enought to shew how it ought to be regarded. In order to which I shall observe, 1, The sincerity and truth of your Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and other Papers on this Subject. 2. Their perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency. 3. The strength of your Reasoning. 4. Your great knowledge in the Constitution of this Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy. 5. The provision you make to secure it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You think it plain from the History of all times. and place,<note place="margin">Their sincerity and truth in History.</note> and of <hi>England</hi> especially, that no Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment has been, or can be <hi>free,</hi> without <hi>the Sword in the hands of the people;</hi> that is, as you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain your selves,<note place="margin">An Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stract of some of the instan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> the <hi>men of property;</hi> and that a <hi>Standing Army</hi> is <hi>Slavery, Popery, Mahometism, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganism, Atheism,</hi> or any thing which they please; Your definition of <hi>a Standing Army, is Horse and Foot rais'd under Commission granted by the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A Letter from the Author of the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a Standing Army. p. 5.</note>
               <hi>with Swords and Pistols, Pikes, and Musquets, Powder, and Ball, to kill men.</hi> Now if it should happen that Bows and Arrows were us'd at any time, and not Musquets, you may help your selves off from some instances of <hi>Standing Armies,</hi> because no Musquets were used, which you bring into the definition: However when you argue for trusting <hi>Arms</hi> only in the hands <hi>of sober,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mil. p. 17.</note>
               <hi>industrious, and understanding Freemen,</hi> to keep to your definition, the Commanders of these <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ought not to be commissioned by the King; but be that as 'twill (since your Scheme for the <hi>Militia</hi> leaves it indifferent,<note place="margin">Militia Reform'd p. 49. p. 22.</note>
               <hi>Whether they be Elected by Lot, or successively appointed by the King;</hi>) yet you will have it, that in all <hi>Free Governments,</hi> and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:185067:8"/>in the <hi>Roman,</hi> as long as the Governments have continued free, the Sword has been in the hands of the people, or Freemen;<note place="margin">Militia Reform'd. p. 19.</note> and that <hi>none but men of Fortune and Property, whose private interest firmly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged them to the publick good, had the honour of ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in their Armies;</hi> for which purpose you load your Margin with pompous Quotations, which may pass upon the unwary for proofs of your assertions.</p>
            <p>And you lay it as a Rule,<note place="margin">Argument p. 4.</note> which you hold to be <hi>universally true, That where-ever the Militia, or Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Strength is, there is, or will be, the Government in a short time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to <hi>England,</hi> you with great triumph <hi>desire to know</hi> of the Patriots,<note place="margin">ib. p. 25.</note>
               <q>How comes an Army ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to our preservation now, and never since the Conquest before? Did ever the prevailing Party in the Wars of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaster,</hi> attempt to keep up a <hi>Standing Army</hi> to support themselves? <hi>No;</hi> you conclude, they had more sense than to Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice their own Liberty, and more honour than to enslave their Country, the more easily to carry on their own Faction; and according to your gift of bringing in your <hi>twice sodden Coleworts,</hi>
               </q> in your History you say, <q>In all the Wars of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caster,</hi> whatever Party prevailed, we don't find they ever attempted to keep up a standing Army; such was the virtue of those times, that they would rather run the hazard of forfeiting their Heads and Estates to the rage of the opposite Party, than certainly enslave their Country, tho they themselves were to be the Tyrants.<note place="margin">p. 3.</note>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In the Argument (which possibly my first Letter may have prevented your repeating as to this matter) "you say, <q>Were not the <hi>Spaniards</hi> as Powerful, as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:185067:9"/>good Soldiers,<note place="margin">Ar. p. 25.</note> and as much our Enemies, as the <hi>French</hi> are now? Was not <hi>Flanders</hi> as near us as <hi>France?</hi> And the Popish Interest in Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi>'s time as strong as the <hi>Jacobite</hi> is now? And yet that most Excellent Princess never dream'd of a <hi>Standing Army,</hi> but thought her surest Empire was to Reign in the Hearts of her Subjects.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Your Argument being something cooler than your History, you could not grace your first attempt, to prove that Land Forces must necessarily destroy our Constitution, with any part of the Reign of <hi>J.</hi> I. a King who scandalously affected the Stile of <hi>Pacific;</hi> and yet, without Arms, waged War with his Subjects, and gain'd ground upon their Liberties.</p>
            <p>Indeed as to <hi>C.</hi> I. you inform the World, That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but want of a Standing Force saved the Nation in his time,<note place="margin">Ar. p. 14. <hi>v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cont.</hi> Hist. p. 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> p. 7.</note> and are positive, if he <hi>had had Five thousand Men beforehand with us,</hi> which is not limited to any <hi>particular part</hi> of his Reign, <hi>the People had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver struck a stroke for their Liberties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You affirm, <q>That this Nation would not suffer our Kings to keep up an Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> tho there were frequent Rebellions there, and by that means their subjection very precarious, <hi>as well knowing they would be in</hi> England <hi>when called for.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the IId, you say, being connived at in keeping a few Guards (which were the first ever known to an <hi>English</hi> King besides his Pentioners and his Beef-Eaters) he insensibly increased their Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,<note place="margin">Id. p. 16.</note> till he left a Body of Men to his Successors great enough to tell the Parliament,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>vid.</hi> Hist. p. 17. <hi>è con.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>he would be no longer bound by the Laws he had Sworn to.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Speaking of the Reign of His present Majesty, with whose Administration you take as much freedom
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:185067:9"/>as with any of his Predecessors, you affirm,<note place="margin">P. 37.</note> That 7877 of his Majesty's present Forces are Foreigners, <hi>which,</hi> according to your great truth and knowledge in History, you say, <hi>is the first Foreign Army that ever set foot in</hi> England, <hi>but as Friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You boldly intimate, That the Officers of all his Majesty's present Forces,<note place="margin">P. 25, 26.</note> ought to be <hi>Attainted of High Treason,</hi> and that Soldiers are now, <hi>against Law, Quartered in all parts of</hi> England, by no other <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> than a <hi>Vote</hi> of the House of Commons to give 350000 <hi>l.</hi> for <hi>Guards</hi> and <hi>Garisons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which Historical assertions and insinuations, with some of their further embelishments, deserve a short examination; and it may be worth enquiry, whether a little ingenuity, or attention, to what you had been informed of not long before, might not have prevented some of your mistakes, both in the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>English</hi> History; as well as an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament might have silenc'd your objection against the Legality of the present Subsistence of a Land Force.</p>
            <p>As to your use of the <hi>Roman</hi> History,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roman</hi> History.</note> you may please to remember instances offered to your obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, whereby it appeared, that That Wise Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, even while they had a Commonwealth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter to <hi>A, B,</hi> &amp;c. p. 26.</note> were far from keeping to your balance, between the <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and artificial strength;</hi> the far greater part of their Armies having been <hi>Auxiliaries:</hi> and that they did not think they could have preserved their Liberties,<note place="margin">Ar. p. 4. <hi>Vid.</hi> Letter to <hi>A, B,</hi> &amp;c. p. 26.</note> without reposing large confidence in great and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous <hi>Generals,</hi> as particularly they did, with good success, in <hi>Pompey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I would gladly know, how long, or in what time since <hi>Rome</hi>'s extending its Dominion beyond the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:185067:10"/>Walls, or Suburbs of the <hi>City,</hi> 'twas such a <hi>Free Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> as you contend for, where <hi>the Sword is in the hands of the People, and all Persons are equally Educated in Civil and Military Discipline.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Militia Reform'd. p. 22.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Since to them who fancy they can comprehend infinity, a Thousand years may seem but as a day; 'Tis an easy leap with you from the <hi>Comitia Curiata</hi> (which according to <hi>Amelius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. p. 32.</note> had no relation to Soldiery) and the <hi>Centuriate Assemblies</hi> of anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Flor.</hi> Prima aetas sub Regibus fuit prope <hi>250</hi> annos quibus circum ipsam matrem suam cum finitimis luctatus est.</note>
               <hi>Established in its Infancy, above</hi> 600 years before Christ (the time of the continuance of which, according to its first Establishment, is wholly uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain) to come to an Order publish'd in the Fourth Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury after Christ, by <hi>Gratian, Valentinian,</hi> and <hi>Theodosius,</hi> which you bring in as a <hi>Rule of listing Freemen only:</hi> but with your usual strain of Reflections, you make it to have had no effect, because the <hi>Emperors at the same time resolv'd to continue Arbitrary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, the Rule you instance in is neither rightly understood, nor applied by you; for the decree which you render, that in our <hi>best Troops</hi> there be no <hi>Slaves</hi> enroll'd,<note place="margin">Inter optimas lectissimorum mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum turmas neminem è numero ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorum dandum esse decernimus neve ex aupona ductum.</note>
               <q>nor <hi>any Servants</hi> out of Houses of Entertainment; is restrain'd to the <hi>best Troops of the choicest or most select Soldiers,</hi> or rather <hi>Horsemen,</hi> among which there were to be no <hi>Servants,</hi> nor any one taken from an House of Entertainment.</q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis manifest that the decree has nothing of your distinction between <hi>Slaves</hi> and <hi>Servants;</hi> nor relates to Common Soldiers▪ but to the best Horse, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably such as made the <hi>Emperors</hi> Horse Guards: but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:185067:10"/>if this decree did extend farther, necessity would have compell'd those Emperors to break it, not for the making themselves absolute, but to defend themselves from the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> who had before that time broken in upon the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire:</hi> but if we confine our selves to the times, while <hi>Rome,</hi> as you would have it, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd your <hi>Free Government;</hi> 'tis certain, that without the help of <hi>Auxiliaries,</hi> and giving the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> privileges to Strangers, they could not have preserv'd so much as the Being of their Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, much less have enlarged it: And that they did not subdue the <hi>Eastern</hi> Nations by the Militia of <hi>Italy:</hi> nor was the Sword first <hi>put into the hands of Servants by the Arbitrary Emperors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Militia Reform'd. p. 69.</note> who durst not <hi>trust men of Property.</hi> Though you, going on with this imagination of your own, impute the shaking off of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, by the <hi>Oriental Countries,</hi> and the Invasion of the <hi>Goths and Vandals,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib.</note> to the Arbitrary disposition of the Emperors, which led 'em to Arm Servants, or others besides <hi>Citizens,</hi> or <hi>Freemen:</hi> 'Tis no matter whether this be true, it makes for your purpose to assert it, and few you think will presume to doubt your Authority. Upon which you would have it believ'd, That till about the time the <hi>Eastern</hi> Nations shook off the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoke, and the Empire was invaded by the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> none but <hi>men of Property</hi> bore Arms for it; and that thus it would have continued but for the Arbitrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of the <hi>Emperors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whoever were to be entrusted with Arms, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the strictest <hi>Roman</hi> Discipline; 'tis certain it ow'd the chief Provisions for its security and greatness, to the Wisdom and Virtue of Kings.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:185067:11"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Florus lib. 1. cap. 3.</note>
               <hi>Tullus Hostilius</hi> first instituted all their Military Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and Art of War; inspired into <hi>Rome</hi> the courage to <hi>rival Alba,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hic omne militarem disciplinam artem{que} bellandi condidit.</note> and power to destroy it. The <hi>Centuriate</hi> Assemblies which you recommend, were first appointed by the elder <hi>Tarquin,</hi> whose Foreign Birth was of no small advantage towards his impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Kingdom: and the inviting Strangers, and transplanting the <hi>Albines,</hi> made no inconsidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble accession to the strength of the <hi>Romans;</hi> which men were not so much for their Birth, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Interest, to preserve the place of their Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement.</p>
            <p>If at their first planting, before the Excesses of some, and Avarice of others, had made unequal Distributions of Property; every Proprietor of abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity serv'd in the War in person; 'tis certain, when one man came to possess as much as One hundred had at the first, he must either have supplied his Quota with himself, and Ninety nine Servants, or Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; or else there must have been but one Soldier, where there had been an hundred.</p>
            <p>This, Gentlemen, Reason might inform you, without consulting History; however, you might have observ'd out of <hi>Velleius Paterculus,</hi> enough to over throw your fancy of the <hi>Roman</hi> Discipline.</p>
            <p>
               <q> The first <hi>Scipio,</hi> says he, open'd the way to the power of the <hi>Romans,</hi> the latter to their Luxury; for the fear of <hi>Carthage</hi> being removed,<note place="margin">Velleius Paterculus <hi>lib. 2.</hi> in principio.</note> and the Emulatrix of Empire taken away; they departed from Virtue, and run over to Vices, not by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, but with a precipitous course: <hi>The Old Discipline was Deserted,</hi> New brought in; the City was turn'd from Watchings to Sleep, <hi>from Arms to Pleasures,</hi> from Business to Idleness: then
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:185067:11"/>
                  <hi>Scipio Nasica</hi> built Porches in the Capitol, <hi>Metellus,</hi> those whichare mentioned before; then <hi>Coeus Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> in the <hi>Cirque</hi> much the pleasantest of them all: And <hi>private Luxury succeeded publick Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence.</hi> Then follow'd the sad and reproachful War in <hi>Spain, Viriathus</hi> being Leader of the Robbers; which was waged with so various fortune, that 'twas for the most part adverse to the <hi>Romans:</hi> But <hi>Viriathus</hi> being slain, rather by the Fraud than Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of <hi>Servilius Coepio;</hi> a more grievous one of the <hi>Numantines</hi> broke out. This City never armed more than Ten thousand of its own Youth.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hoec urbs nunqnam plur a quam decem mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia proprias juventutis armavit. <hi>Argument p. 7.</hi>
               </note>Now to judge whether your Scheme of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth is practicable here, since the encrease of Arts, Sciences, and Luxury; apply it only to your own pattern, and consider whether <hi>a general exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of the best of the people of</hi> Rome <hi>in the use of Arms, was the only bulwark of their Liberties?</hi> and whether <hi>in those days there was no difference</hi> between <hi>the Citizen, the Soldier, and the Husbandman?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis observable, that this ancient Author says, that the <hi>Romans</hi> in no time arm'd more <hi>than ten thousand</hi> of its own Youth: And as the Learned <hi>Vossius</hi> observes,<note place="margin">Gerardi Vossi Notae in Paterculums <hi>upon this passage.</hi> Hoec urbs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Florus autem &amp; Orosius plus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munt dimidio. Nam de quaternis solum milibus loquuntur.</note>
               <q>
                  <hi>Appian</hi> lessens this Number by 2000. <hi>Florus</hi> and <hi>Orosius,</hi> take away more than half, for they speak only of <hi>four thousand.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If the whole Commonwealth of <hi>Rome</hi> was, as you imagine, but <hi>one form'd Militia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Argument p. 7.</note> it must needs have had a much greater body of its own Youth, than the highest of these computations; but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was the number of their own Forces, they could not always maintain the <hi>seat of Empire;</hi> but once
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:185067:12"/>were forc'd to change it for <hi>Corfinium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Velleius Paterc. <hi>lib. 2. Sect. 16.</hi> Caput impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii sui Corfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium lege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> where they must have skulk'd till they had been destroyed, but for very great men at their head, and the putting Arms into the hands of <hi>Strangers,</hi> or others, not before trusted with them.</p>
            <p>For further evidence that the <hi>Roman</hi> Wars were not carried on only by the Citizens of <hi>Rome;</hi> Permit me to Transcribe part of what <hi>Velleius Paterculus</hi> says of the War commenced by the <hi>Asculans,</hi> and followed by the <hi>Marsians,</hi> and the generality of the people of <hi>Italy,</hi> because of their being denied the Freedom of the <hi>City.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Quorum ut fortuna a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trox ita causa fuit justissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma: petebant enim eam civitatem cujus imperium armis tuebantur: per om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes annos at{que} omnb ella duplici numero se militum equitum{que} fungi: ne{que} in ejus civitatis jus recipi, quae per eos in id ipsum pervenisset fastigium, per quod homines ejus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem &amp; gentis &amp; san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis, ut exernos alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos{que} fastidire posset.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whose Fortune,</hi> says he, <hi>as 'twas severe, so their cause was most just; for they demanded the freedom of that</hi> City, <hi>whose Empire they had defended by their Arms: They represented that throughout all Years, and all Wars, they serv'd with a</hi> double <hi>Quota of Foot and Horse: and yet were not admitted to the right of that</hi> City, <hi>which by their means had arrived to that very height, that it could contemn men' of the same both Nation and Blood, as Foreigners and Strangers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:185067:12"/>
            <p>Thus it may appear, that <hi>Rome</hi> was never for any considerable time such a <hi>free Government,</hi> as you labour for, nor indeed could be: And 'twill appear, that you are neither more fair, nor more fortunate in the <hi>English,</hi> than you have been in the <hi>Roman</hi> Story.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Saxon</hi> Times, as I had observ'd, before the great encrease of Trade, the ballance of Power was on the side of Property, and that in Land; that Polity was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable for the Peope in those Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances; but as 'twould be the work of Ages,<note place="margin">A short Account of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Provisions and Establishments for defence of this Kingdom, and of the trust for that end repos'd in the Crown.</note> to reduce us to those Circumstances; so 'twould be to make us capable of that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del; and to that end there must be a new distribution of Property, upon which, you, Gentlemen, no doubt would propose to your selves a share according to your large Merits. But even then no man was obliged to go to the War in his own person, 'twas enough if he found a sufficient man in his room; for which I may refer you to <hi>Doomesday</hi> Book, that great Record of the time of <hi>William</hi> I.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doomesday.</hi> Wirecestre scire. In civ. Wirecest. quando Rex in hostem pergit siquis edicto ejus vocatus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manserit; si ita liber home est ut habeat socam suam &amp; sacam &amp; cum terrâ suâ possit ire quo voluerit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> where speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the then Ancient Custom in the City of <hi>Worcester,</hi> it shews that when the <hi>King</hi> went to the War, if any one, who was so free, that he had suit and service of Court, and could go with his Land, whither he would, staid at home after Summons; he was to be in the King's mercy for all his Land: If he was a<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. First Letter to <hi>A, B. C.</hi> from p. 16, 17, 18.</note>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:185067:13"/>Freeholder of any Lord, and his Lord found a man in his stead, after he had been summon'd by his Lord; he was to pay his Lord 40 <hi>s.</hi> if no body went for him, still he was to pay 40 <hi>s.</hi> to his Lord, and the Lord to pay as much to the King.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Trinoda necessitas.</note>In those time, besides the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> rate,<note place="margin">Vid. Regist. Abind. in Bib. Cot. Claud 9.</note> or the general incidents to Land (unless such as were parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly exempted by Charters pass'd in the <hi>Great Councils,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cart. E. 1. <hi>ante</hi> Con{que} Except. <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> viz. <hi>Expeditione pontis arcis{que} re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par. sic.</hi> ib. Cart. Ed. Conf ib. Cart. <hi>Ethelredi communi labore,</hi> &amp;c.</note>) call'd, The <hi>Threefold necessity.</hi> 1. The <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi> 2. The Repair of Bridges. 3. Of Forts and Castles. There were long before the reputed Conquest, express reservations of Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Tenures.</p>
            <p>Long since notice has been taken of the Charter of <hi>Kenulph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. White's Sacred Law. <hi>p.</hi> 148. 12 <hi>Cum scutis.</hi> Vid. Bib. Col. sub. Effigie Claudii 9.</note> King of <hi>Mercia</hi> to <hi>Abington,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cum Regis Edicto in annalibus anno arentur quot de Episcopiis quotve de Abbatiis ad publicam rem tuendam milites, si forte huic causae propellendae contigeret exigerentur eisdem donativis prius retentis Abbas mansiones possessioni Eccles. pertin. inde delegavit: edicto cui{que} tenore parendi de suae portioniis mansione. Quae possessio nes ab eis habitae fuerunt quos Thanos dicunt, &amp; in bello Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stingis occubuerant.</note> exmpting them from all Services, but the expedition with 12 Shield-bearers; which according to the Register of <hi>Abington</hi> in the <hi>Cotton Library</hi> were so many <hi>Thanes</hi> or <hi>Knights:</hi> That Register, speaking of the number of <hi>Knights</hi> Enrolled in <hi>Doomesday</hi> Book, as charged upon <hi>Bishopricks,</hi> and Abbies; shews, <q>that the Donatives or Grants having been before kept in possession; that Abbot alienated from the Church, some <hi>Mansions,</hi> Houses with portions of Land; every one being appointed the tenour of his Service for his propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Which possessions had been enjoyed by them whom they call</hi> Thanes, <hi>and had dyed in the battle at</hi> Hastings.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:185067:13"/>
            <p>Thus in <hi>Doomesday</hi> Book we find that <hi>Ayulf</hi> the Chamberlain held<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Domesday.</hi> Dorset Terra Ayulfi Camerar. Ipse A. tenet Odeton. Brusi tenuit miles Regis Edw.</note>
               <hi>Odeton</hi> in <hi>Dorset<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> which had been possess'd by <hi>Brusi</hi> King <hi>Edwards</hi> Knight, (the same as I take it with<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bedefordscire f. 216.</hi> Tovi Huscarle Regis Edwardi.</note>
               <hi>Huscarle</hi>) and <hi>Godwin,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Malms. f. 81.</hi> Servitium mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litum quos per Angliam habebant Regi contraderent.</note> and his Son <hi>Harold,</hi> were by judgment of the <hi>Great Council,</hi> to deliver or assign over to that King, the Service of all their <hi>Knights</hi> throughout <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Antiquity of these Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and other incidents to tenure, may appear by<note n="d" place="margin">Vid. Original. Cart. in Bib. Cot.</note>
               <hi>Wulfere</hi> the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> King's Charter of exemption to <hi>Medhamsted</hi> or <hi>Peterborough,</hi> in the year 664.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cum coeteris optimatibus &amp; Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stris Regis.</note>
               <hi>Wulfere</hi>'s Charer, subscrib'd by several of his Peers, and consented to by the rest of the <hi>Great men,</hi> and the King's <hi>Thanes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ab omni Scotto &amp; geldo, &amp; ab omni auxilio Regum, Vicecomitum, &amp; omnium Ministralium suorum: &amp; Schirar. &amp; hund. placitis &amp; que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relis, Wardpenii, &amp; Boroupenii, &amp; Lestage, Wrec. &amp; ab omnibus ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus castellorum, parcorum, &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muum &amp; de claustur &amp; ab omni Careio, &amp; summagio, &amp; navigio, &amp; regalium dom. edificatione &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimoda operatione. Et silvae eor. ad pred. opera vel ad aliqua alia nulle modo capiantur. Precipimus etiam quod pred monasterium &amp; dominica sint lib. &amp; quiet ab omni domina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione &amp; exactione Com. Baron. Vice-comitum, &amp; Ministral, suor.</note>
               <q>exempts the <hi>Monks</hi> of that place, and their <hi>Demesns</hi> from every scot and geld, and from every aid of <hi>Kings, Sheriffs,</hi> and of all their Ministers, Hidage, and <hi>Dane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geld,</hi> from the pleas and plaints of <hi>Shires</hi> and <hi>Hundreds, Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penny, Boroughpenny,</hi> and <hi>Lestage, Wrec,</hi> and from all Works and Enclosures of <hi>Castles, Parks,</hi> and Houses, and from all <hi>Carriage,</hi> and <hi>Summage,</hi> and <hi>Shipping,</hi> and Building of the King's Houses, and all work. And their Woods were not to be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:185067:14"/>made use of, for the said or other Works.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Besides, 'tis particularly required, that the said Monastery and Demesns, be free and acquitted from all domination and exaction of Earls, <hi>Barons,</hi> She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs, and their Officers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But all the Lands which were not thus exempted, were subject to the incidents abovementioned; and some were over and above those incidents, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly obliged to serve the King, or the Lord, who was the King's immediate Tenant; not but that before the reputed Conquest, 'tis to be believed that the number of such as were bound to particular Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were much less,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> 1st. Let <hi>p.</hi> 20.</note> than they were after the large distribution of forfeited and other Lands, made by <hi>William</hi> the I. to those who assisted him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering his Right, which many of the <hi>English</hi> did.</p>
            <p>'Tis generally<note n="*" place="margin">Selden <hi>'s Tit. of Honour.</hi> f. <hi>573. 60215. Knights Fees. Doomes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</hi> Leicestr. Si verò per mare in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes ibat mittebant quatuor equos. <hi>Ib. Colchster.</hi> Ad victum soldariorum Regis ad expeditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem terrae vel maris <hi>Ib.</hi> Et hoc fit si Rex sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darios ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerit vel expeditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem fecerit.</note> thought, that <hi>W.</hi> I. had more than 600000, which before the time of the great Survey, were obliged to serve him in his Wars; though the Author of the Red Book in the Exchequer, makes the number but 22000. What was the proportion of every single Person, or Body Politick, towards the War, as I take it, cannot now be known by <hi>Doomesday-Book;</hi> but depended upon their Grants: though the proportions of some are there enter'd: Thus the City of <hi>Leicester,</hi> now but a Borough Town, was to send <hi>Four Horses to carry Arms,</hi> or things necessary, as far as <hi>London, upon a Naval Expedition.</hi> The Town of <hi>Colchester</hi> in <hi>Essex</hi> us'd to pay 6 <hi>d. per</hi> House for the subsistence of the King's Soldiers for Land Service, and that while there were Soldiers in pay, though no actual expedition. The Town of <hi>Stanford</hi> was geldable for the Land and Sea-Service, and <hi>Danegeld,</hi> at the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:185067:14"/>rate of 12 Hundreds and an half; where the finding the men was plainly left to the discretion of the King and his Officers; and indeed, unless 'twere generally so, 'twill be difficult to believe, that the Ancient <hi>Historians</hi> give a true account, when they represent <hi>Doomesday-Book</hi> as an entry,<note place="margin">Inter al. Brompton <hi>f.976.20.W.I.</hi> Quot hidae <hi>i. e.</hi> jugera uni aratro per annum sufficientia in unaqua{que} villâ essent, &amp; quantum terrae quis{que} Baronum suorum possidebat Inquiri etiam fecit quot feodati milites, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> how many <hi>Knights</hi> or <hi>Soldiers</hi> the <hi>Clergy</hi> was to furnish as well as the <hi>Laity;</hi> and yet the general Entry is only that Lands were <hi>geldable,</hi> at so many <hi>Hides,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wendover M. S. in Bib. Cot. sub Effigie Claudii de Ann. 1070.</note> or the like.</p>
            <p>Indeed,<note place="margin">Episcopatus quo{que} &amp; Abbatias omnesquae Baronias tenebant &amp; eatinus ab omni servitio saeculari libertatem habuerant sub servitute statuit mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litari, irrotulans singulos Episcopatus &amp; Abbatias pro voluntate suâ, quot milites sibi &amp; succes. suis hostili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis tempore voluit à singulis exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri, &amp; rotulos hujus Ecclesiasticae ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitutis ponens in Thesauris, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> it seems by <hi>Roger</hi> of <hi>Wendover,</hi> who wrote before <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Paris</hi> That <hi>W.</hi> I. in the 4th of his Reign, put under Military Service, all <hi>Bishopricks</hi> and <hi>Abbies</hi> that held <hi>Baronies,</hi> enrolling eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Bishoprick</hi> and <hi>Abby</hi> in the Exchequer, with the charge of so many Knights, or men, as he thought fit to be us'd in time of War.</p>
            <p>Whether the Charter of <hi>H.</hi> 1. to<note n="*" place="margin">Cart. Mon. El. in Bib. Cot f. 127. B. Cart. <hi>H.</hi> 1.</note>
               <hi>Ely</hi> relates to this Entry in the Exchequer of <hi>W.</hi> I.; or to the <hi>Great Survey</hi> made at the latter end of his Reign, I need not determine: but some of the words of that Charter I think very material to our present Subject.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText>
                  <body>
                     <div type="charter">
                        <div xml:lang="lat" type="original_charter">
                           <opener>
                              <signed>H. Rex Anglor.</signed>
                              <salute>Com' Vic' &amp; omnibus fidel. suis Francis &amp; Anglis totius Angliae salutem. </salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>Sciatis
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:185067:15"/>quia volo, &amp; concedo, &amp; praecipio ut omnes illi Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rones, &amp; Vavasores, qui terras illas tenent quas Carta mea Wintoniae de Thesauro meo, testatur fuisse juratas temporis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris mei, ad pacem Eccles. de Ely, recognoscant eas &amp; teneant de praed' Eccles. &amp; Episc. de Ely amodo &amp; in perpetuum: faciendo inde Ecclesiae ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitium militiae secundùm tenuras, &amp; secundum hoc quod servitia statuta sunt. Et ita quod Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; Vavasores, easdem terras tenentes quieti sint erga me &amp; alios Dominos suos, de tanto servitio quantum inde Episc. &amp; Eccles. praed' facere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerint, in statuto servitio militiae.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div xml:lang="eng" type="translation">
                           <pb n="27" facs="tcp:185067:15"/>
                           <opener>
                              <signed>Henry <hi>King of the</hi> English</signed>
                              <salute>
                                 <hi>to the</hi> Earls, Barons, <hi>and all faithful Subjects,</hi> French <hi>and</hi> English, <hi>Greeting.</hi>
                              </salute>
                           </opener>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Know you,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:185067:15"/>that I will, and grant, and command, That all those</hi> Barons <hi>and</hi> Vavasors, <hi>who hold those Lands which my Charter-Roll of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer at</hi> Winchester, <hi>testifies to have been sworn in the time of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to preserve the peace of the Church of</hi> Ely, <hi>hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth and for ever recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize and hold them of the said Church, and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of</hi> Ely: <hi>doing for them to the Church</hi> Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Service, <hi>according to their Tenures, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Services which are</hi> appointed. <hi>And so that the</hi> Barons <hi>and</hi> Vavasors, <hi>holding those Lands, be acquitted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, and other Lords, of so much Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as they ought from thence to perform to the said</hi> Bishop and Church, <hi>according to the appointed</hi> Military Service.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:185067:15"/>
            <p>They who were thus to serve the King in his Wars,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. in Doomesday,</hi> distinctions between Lands or Houses, Gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantes, and others.</note> as Tenants of the Church, or Lay-Lords, were of the nature of a <hi>Standing Force,</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison with those who either were <hi>geldable,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Doomesday,</hi> Dorsete in Brideport <hi>T. R. E.</hi> erant <hi>120</hi> domus &amp; ad omne servitium Regis defendebant se &amp; gel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dabant pro 5 hidis scil ad opus Huscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium Regis dimid. mar. argenti.</note> or chargeable,<note place="margin">So Doomesday. Salop. In civitate Scropesberie sunt <hi>252.</hi> Burgenses, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> dicunt Angli Burgenses scropesberie multum grave esse quod ipsi reddant totum geldum sicut reddebatur <hi>T. R. E.</hi> Quamvis castellum Comes occupaverit &amp; <hi>51</hi> masuras &amp; aliae <hi>50</hi> masurae sunt wastae &amp; <hi>43</hi> Franciginae burgenses teneant masuras geldantes <hi>T. R. E.</hi>
               </note> according to the quantity of their Lands, to the maintenance of these, beyond the times that their tenures requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their Service; or other Soldiers that the King should raise; as also in comparison of the <hi>Socmanni,</hi> free So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cagers, or the <hi>Alodiaries,</hi> under the <hi>Thanes</hi> or <hi>Barons,</hi> such as for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, <hi>Ednod</hi> and <hi>Edwi</hi> were, in the time of the <hi>Confessor,</hi> and after, and their Heir <hi>Cole,</hi> who paid Relief to Earl <hi>William.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Doomesday Hantesc.</hi> Terra Tainor Regis Subberie tenuerunt <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod</hi> &amp; <hi>Edwi</hi> in alodio de Rege <hi>Edw.</hi> &amp; post mortem ejus: ipsimet quo{que} mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rui. Quidam vero proximus eorum Cola, redemit terram de W. Comite. Modò tenet eam Walterius in vademo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio de filio Cole de Basinge.</note> These neither held their Lands by Military Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, nor were they, as I take it, <hi>geldable;</hi> and yet by virtue of the <hi>Confessor's</hi> Law, Declaratory of the Common Law of the Kingdom, were obliged to find<note n="†" place="margin">Vid Leges Ed. Tit. Greve.</note> Arms accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their real and personal E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Inter al. Vid. Rot. Pat:</hi> 13 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>pars 1. d.</hi> 28. such a commission to array men between the Towns of <hi>Saltess</hi> and <hi>Fowey.</hi> Rot. Parl. 6 E. 3. <hi>N.</hi> 18. such Commissions referred to and allowed.</note> to produce 'em at the <hi>Wapentakes,</hi> or Hundred Courts; and employ 'em for the <hi>defence of the Kingdom:</hi> in which they were to be aided by all who lived under the <hi>King's</hi> protection and peace. For the maintaining which, our Kings have originally been entrust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with power, by commissions of <hi>Array,</hi> to raise not only <hi>Freemen,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:185067:16"/>but Servants and <hi>Villains:</hi> whom they listed, and continued together upon Emergencies.</p>
            <p>Besides, the Kings, as I take it, before the time of <hi>W.</hi> I. us'd not only to have Horses with their Equipage, for the Reliefs of Heirs that were of full Age at the Death of their Ancestors, who held of the Crown by Knights Service; but the custody of the Heirs that were Minors; and the providing for the Service: These and other Soldiers they used to keep in Garison. Many of the Soldiers here in the <hi>Confessor's</hi> time were Foreigners; and such even in the time of <hi>W.</hi> I. if we believe the Register of <hi>Abbingdon,</hi> were a great benefit and protection to them that desired to live in peace. Speaking of the Affairs of <hi>Abbingdon</hi> in those times, the Register has these words:</p>
            <p>In primordio autem sui adventus in Abbatiam non nisi armator septus manumilitum alicubi pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedebat,<note place="margin">Regist. Ab. in Bib. Got. Sup.</note> quidem necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio multae enim novita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes conjuratorum indies passim contra Regem &amp; Regnum ejus ebullientes universos in Angliâ se tueri cogebant. Tunc Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingaforde &amp; Oxeneforde &amp; Wildesore, caeterisque locis castella pro Regno servando compacta unde huic Abbatiae militum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubias ad ipsum Wildesore
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:185067:16"/>oppidum habendas Regio imperio jussum. Quare tali in articulo hujus for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunae, milites transmarini in Angliam venientes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vore colebantur precipuo.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:185067:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>When the first came to the</hi> Abby, <hi>he went no whither without being guarded with a number of Arm'd Soldiers: Indeed of necessity; for many new Conspiracies daily break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out every where against the</hi> King <hi>and his Kingdom, compell'd all people in</hi> England <hi>to be upon their guard. Then Castles were built at</hi> Wallingford, <hi>and</hi> Oxford, <hi>and</hi> Windsor, <hi>and other places, for the safety of the Kingdom, whence it was commanded this</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:185067:16"/>Abby <hi>by the King's Edict,</hi> to keep Watch and Ward with Soldiers, to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Town of <hi>Windsor. Wherefore at such a point of time,</hi> Foreign <hi>Soldiers coming into</hi> England <hi>were had in chief esteem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tunc temporis milites quidam Abendonenses, Regis pro negotio Normaniam missi, cum maris in medio remigrarent a piratis capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Quorum unus Hermerus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, necdum alicujus terrae portionem adeptus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> unde in futurum victitet.</note> The same Register shews, that Foreign Soldiers were maintain'd there in Garison, and that one of them having no Estate in <hi>England,</hi> had, by the King's command, a corrody or subsistence there during Life.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Milites hujus Eccles. pene omnes proficisci jubentur</note> In a War with the <hi>Scots,</hi> the Abbot of <hi>Abbington</hi> attended <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> the King's Son, as 'tis proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with the Soldiers either in Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison, or holding of the <hi>Abby;</hi> the Register is express,<note n="c" place="margin">Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strare victualia Regis-imperio juben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> that upon an Expedition against the <hi>Welsh,</hi> almost all that Churches Soldiers were commanded to go; and a great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my being prepared upon an Invasion threatned by the <hi>Danes,</hi> all the <hi>Bishopricks</hi> and <hi>Abbies</hi> were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to supply it with Victuals; which yet I take not to have been an Arbitrary imposition; but in pursuance of the custom before that King's Reign, agreeable to what we find in <hi>Doomesday-book,</hi> of the <hi>Customs</hi> of <hi>Berkshire.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:185067:17"/>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <p>Quando geldum daba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <hi>T. R. E.</hi> communiter per totam Berochscire dabat hida 3 <hi>d.</hi> ob. ante Nativ. dom. &amp; tantum ad Pentecosten. Si Rex mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebat alicubi exercitum, de 5 hidis tantum unus miles ibat: &amp; ad ejus victum vel stipendium de unaqua{que} hidâ dabant ei 4 <hi>s.</hi> ad duos menses. Hos verò denarios Regi non mittebant, sed militibus dabant.</p>
            </q>
            <q xml:lang="eng">
               <p>
                  <hi>When a Geld was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in general throughout</hi> Berkshire, <hi>one hide gave</hi> 3 <hi>d</hi> ¼ <hi>at</hi> Christmas, <hi>and as much at</hi> Whitsontide. <hi>If the King sent an Army any whither, from 5 hides, only one Soldier went, and from every hide they gave him</hi> 4 <hi>s. for</hi> 2 <hi>Months for his dyet, or pay. But this money they did not send the King, but gave the Soldiers.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>It seems to have been the particular privilege of <hi>Berkshire,</hi> to have had the paying its own Soldiers; but as it should seem, other Counties sent the money to the King, or his Officers, who rais'd the men, or caus'd them to be arrayed. But Gelds for the War, and particularly <hi>Hidage,</hi> so far at least as went to the pay of Soldiers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Leges In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e c. <hi>70</hi> De victu sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedit. <hi>and Vid. Glos. Tit. Geld.</hi> Vicinos Werra, suos exercitibus &amp; geldis continuis vexabat.</note> cannot but be thought to have been exacted by virtue of a Parliamentary Establishment, before the reputed Conquest. And to me it seems, that the Law of King <hi>Ina,</hi> setting a proportion of Meat and Drink upon every Ten Hides of Land, relates to the Army. In which sense <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Huntington,</hi> cited by the Learned <hi>Spelman,</hi> says of <hi>W.</hi> II. "He vex'd his Neighbours with War; his "own People with Armies, and continual <hi>Gelds.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:185067:17"/>
            <p>These were such as <hi>Bracton</hi> calls <hi>common Prestations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bracton lib. 2. c. 16.</hi> Sunt etiam quaedam communes prestationes quae servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia non di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur nec de consuctudine veniunt, nisi cum necessis as intervenerit val cum Rex venerit, sicut sunt hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagia, corragia, carvagia &amp; alia plura de necessitate &amp; consensu communi totius regni introducta.</note> in contradistinction to Services coming of course; these, according to him, not being due, but in case of necessity, or when the King went to War; and were introduced by <hi>Necessity, and the Common Consent of the whole Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any man think that I impose upon him with my Conjectures, in relation to the ancient <hi>Gelds,</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly <hi>Hidage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Lib. Rub. in Scio p. Gerv. Tilb. Temp. H. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> he may with me consult the <hi>Red Book</hi> in the Exchequer; which speaking of Pyrates from the Islands round about, which used to infest and depopulate the Maritime Places, and particularly the <hi>Danes,</hi> says,</p>
            <p>Ad hos igitur arcendos à Regibus Anglicus statu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum est, ut de singulis hidis regni, jure quodam perpetuo, duo solidi argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tei solverentur, in usus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorum fortium, qui perlu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strantes &amp; jugiter excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantes maritima, impetum hostium reprimerent. Quia igitur principaliter pro Danis institutus est hic reditus, Danegeldum vel Danegeldus dicitur.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore for the repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling these, 'twas ordain'd by Kings of</hi> England, <hi>That</hi> Two Shillings in Silver from every Hide of the Kingdom, <hi>should be paid</hi> by a sort of Perpetual Right, for the use of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Men, who carefully viewing and constantly guarding the Maritime Places, <hi>might resist the Insults of the Enemies. Because therefore this Rent or Tax was instituted chiefly by reason of the</hi> Danes, <hi>'tis call'd</hi> Danegeld.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:185067:18"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Leges Ed. Conf de Danegeld.</note>The Confessor's Law agrees with this in Substance, only makes the Annual Payment but 12 <hi>d. per</hi> Hide, and says that every Church, and all the Demesne Land of the Church, us'd to be free from it.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Gervace</hi> of <hi>Tilbury</hi> it appears to have been a constant Annual Payment, till the Power and good Government of <hi>Will.</hi> I. suppressed those Pyrates. That Great Prince, (who has been unduly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented as acting like a Conqueror of this Land, as that Author has it,</p>
            <p>Noluit hoc ut annuum solvi quod fuerat urgente necessitate bellicae tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pestatis exactum. Nec tamen omnino propter inopinatos casus dimitti. Rarò ergo temporibus ejus vel successor. ipsius solutum est; hoc est, cum ab exteris gentibus bella vel ☞ opiniones bellorum insurgebant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Would not that this should be paid as</hi> Annual, <hi>which had been exacted by urgent Necessity in time of War; nor yet that it should be discharg'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of sudden Accidents. Therefore it has seldom been paid in the times of him or his Successors; that is, when there arose Wars from Foreign Nations, or <hi>apprehensions</hi> of Wars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Selden's Mare Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sum lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note>Mr. <hi>Selden</hi> tells us, That this Tribute or Tax for the Custody of the Sea, which he shews to take in Land as well as Sea-Service, us'd to be paid under <hi>W.</hi> I. <hi>W.</hi> II. <hi>H.</hi> I. King <hi>Stephen;</hi> and that it <hi>appears by the Accounts in the Exchequer,</hi> that 'twas sometimes paid under <hi>H.</hi> II.</p>
            <p>He observes farther, That after that had ceas'd, some other way of the like nature was frequently us'd; that Soldiers Wages, and other Provisions for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:185067:18"/>the defence of the Sea,<note place="margin">Pro mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus patriis usurpari est solita, ne stipendia &amp; commeatus tuendae regni Angliae provinciae maritimae omnino deessent.</note> and Maritime Parts of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> might not be wholly wanting.</p>
            <p>And he cites a Record of the Court of Common-Pleas, 25 <hi>E.</hi> I. mentioning Land <hi>agisted,</hi> or assessed for the <hi>Custody of the Sea;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Scimus quidem eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ad co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piarum in littore ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restrium stipendia &amp; commeatus, sub id tempus nomine maris corrogari.</note> under which Name he as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures us upon his own knowledge, that Wages and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions for <hi>Land-Forces</hi> on the Sea-side, were collected.</p>
            <p>As some of these Taxes were often gathered with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an immediate National Consent, to that very Tax or <hi>Geld:</hi> 'tis no wonder that the People of <hi>England</hi> would not be satisfied till they obtained <hi>King John's Charter,</hi> which provides, That no <hi>Escuage</hi> nor <hi>Aid,</hi> unless for particular <hi>Services,</hi> shall be raised without Consent of the <hi>Common Council</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> of which <hi>Common Council,</hi> the <hi>City of London,</hi> and other Cities, the Cinque-Ports, Boroughs, and <hi>Vills</hi> (as appears by that Charter, and at last is yielded by Dr. <hi>Brady</hi>) were to be a part.</p>
            <p>This however, as it seems, was but declaratory of the Law, as 'twas as early as the time of <hi>H.</hi> II.;<note place="margin">In nullo dissimilis.</note> for the great Charter of <hi>H.</hi> III. which as <hi>Matthew Paris</hi> observes, was in nothing unlike to, or differing from <hi>King John</hi>'s, has no other provision about this,<note place="margin">Scutagium de caetero capiatur si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cut capi consuevit tempore H. avi sui. Vid. Jus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glor. ab an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquo p. <hi>149</hi>
               </note> but that <hi>Escuage</hi> should be taken, as was accustomed in the time of <hi>H.</hi> II. But neither of these Charters seem'd to relate to <hi>Tallage,</hi> which was not of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of an Aid, but a Duty upon the King's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mesnes; and therefore was not within the meaning of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:185067:19"/>the Charter of <hi>W.</hi> I. which declares that all the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the whole Monarchy of his Kingdom, shall hold their Lands and Possessions well and in Peace, free from unjust Exaction, and <hi>all Tallage,</hi> except their <hi>Free Service, which of Right</hi> they owe, and are bound to perform; and as is appointed and granted them by him hereditarily for ever, by the <hi>Common Council</hi> of his whole Kingdom. One of the Free Services of Demesne Lands, <hi>Tallage</hi> certainly was. The Grievance of which occasioned the Statute in the time of <hi>E.</hi> I. <hi>de Tallaguio non concedendo,</hi> which provided that no <hi>Tallage</hi> or Aid be laid or levied, without the Consent of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet this seems not absolutely to have taken away that Power which had been exercised by the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> to compel men to find Soldiers at their own Charge; to resist Enemies upon the Borders of <hi>England,</hi> or to keep Soldiers in Garisons, or to guard the Sea Coasts; which occasioned the Law 25. <hi>E.</hi> III.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stat.</hi> 25. <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> whereby 'twas <q>
                  <hi>accorded and assented,</hi> that no man shall be constrain'd to find <hi>Men of Arms, Hoblers,</hi> nor <hi>Archers,</hi> other than those which <hi>hold by such Servics;</hi> if it be not by <hi>common Assent and Grant made in Parliament.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The former ways of supplying Emergencies failing, our Kings, upon representing the Charges of keeping the Marches of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> and of great Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons both at home and abroad, and the like, had, besides the Revenues of the Crown, which were then very large, frequent Grants from their People, under several denominations, as Subsidies, Fifteenths, Tenths, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for the <hi>Defence of the</hi> Kingdom; which ordinarily they and their Counsel were to provide for, according to the best of their Judgments. If you
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:185067:19"/>suppose that this was to be without keeping up any Standing Forces, even in Garisons, unless in time of actual War; you may as well imagine that when <hi>Tunnage</hi> and <hi>Poundage</hi> were granted for the defence of the Seas, 'twas not intended that any Naval Force should be provided in times of Peace. The securing of which-by such wasy as the King pleases, the<note n="*" place="margin">Stat. <hi>7.</hi> E. <hi>2.</hi> Vid. Stat. ed. An. <hi>1529.</hi> p. <hi>41.</hi> Nous eiont dit que a nous appent, &amp;c. defendre fortement des armes, &amp; tout autre force, contre nostre pees a toutz les foitz que nos plerra.</note>
               <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> 7. <hi>E.</hi> II. recognize to belong to the King by reason of his <hi>Royal Seignory;</hi> and that they are bound to aid him therein as there is occasion.</p>
            <p>Agreeably to this, 'twas usual at the beginning of Parliaments, to have Proclamations, That no body should come armed within the <hi>City of Londond,</hi> or the <hi>Suburbs,</hi> or <hi>other Places about the City,</hi> or Palace of <hi>Westminster, except the King's People deputed by him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Rot. Stat. <hi>16. E. 3. n. 13.</hi> Forspris les gentz no stre sur le Roy, queux il voudra deputer ou per son commandment serront deputez pur la gard de la pees es ditz lieux: &amp; forspris les Ministers le Roy solone la form de lestat. de Northampton.</note>
               <hi>or his command, for the keeping his Peace there,</hi> and <hi>except his Officers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This which you, Gentlemen, would take to be a putting Both Houses of <hi>Parliament</hi> into the Power of the King (who according to your Infallible Maxim would use it to their destruction) is declared to be according to the Statute of <hi>Northampton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But since you are so positive that till <hi>C.</hi> II. none of our Kings, unless <hi>R.</hi> II. had any Standing Force, but in time of War, and particularly that no such thing was <hi>ever</hi> attempted by either Party that prevailed <hi>in the Wars of York and Lancaster;</hi>
               <note place="margin">History sup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> one would think, if you had any degree of ingenuity or attention, you
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:185067:20"/>would have had some consideration of the Objection from 13000 Archers granted by Parliament, in the 31 st of <hi>H.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> 1st. <hi>Let. p.</hi> 30. <hi>citing Rot. Parl.</hi> 12. <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>n</hi> 41.</note> VI. to continue together for half a year, and the same Annual Number for two Years succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively, 12 &amp; 13 of <hi>E.</hi> IV. That the 13000 Archers granted to <hi>H.</hi> VI. were not raised with regard to any present Foreign War, or Domestick Disturbance in near prospect, is plain by the Circumstances of the Time;<note place="margin">Vid. Rot. Parl. <hi>31.</hi> H. <hi>6. Jack Cade</hi> and others at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted.</note> it being after <hi>Jack Cade</hi>'s Rebellion had been quell'd, and when <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> who had before that time intrusted only his chief Confidents with his Aiming at the Crown, having like the <hi>Yorkists</hi> of this Age, cloak'd his Designs with pretence of Zeal for the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> That Claim exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined in the Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon a Treasonable Opinion against signing the Association.</note> was, through the Treachery of some, and Folly of others, chosen <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector</hi> of the Kingdom: which laid the chief founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Publick Calamities that attended his Perjurous, and to him Fatal Claim of a Divine Right, contrary to his most solemn Declarations and Oath.</p>
            <p>But whatever may be gathered from the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of the Time, the Act it self shews, that the Provision had regard to no present Danger; for the raising the 13000 men was respited for two Years;<note place="margin">Rot. Partl. <hi>31.</hi> H. <hi>6.</hi> n. <hi>15</hi>
               </note>
               <q>Unless, as the Act says, it please the King to labour in his own Person for the <hi>Defence</hi> aforesaid; or else that <hi>great and evident Cause, concerning or touching the Defence</hi> aforesaid, <hi>happen</hi> within the said two Years, and <hi>that by the</hi> warning of Three Months.</q>
            </p>
            <p>It appears by the Act 12 <hi>E.</hi> 4. to have been the judgment or apprehension of that Parliament, that by the Stat. 31. <hi>H.</hi> 6. there was a power vested in the Crown, at any time when 'twas found necessary for the <hi>defence</hi> of the Kingdom, to call so many toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for once at least, at the charge of the People:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:185067:20"/>and therefore when they grant <hi>E.</hi> 4. the like num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for a year, they pray that it may please q]the King to <hi>remit and release</hi> for <hi>him</hi> his <hi>Heirs</hi> and <hi>Successors,</hi> to the <hi>Commons</hi> their <hi>Heirs and Successors,</hi> all <hi>right</hi> Exaction and Demand, for the Charge and finding of 13000 men granted to <hi>H.</hi> 6. during the time of an half year.</p>
            <p>And one of the inducements to their grant of 13000 Archers to <hi>E.</hi> 4. as appears by the <hi>Preamble,</hi> was his <q>having reduced the <hi>Realm</hi> and his true Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the same,<note place="margin">12 <hi>E.</hi> 4. <hi>N.</hi> 10.</note>
                  <hi>out of the dangerous chances of Battel, into the prosperous and most desired Estate of Peace.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But then to secure the happy state of peace, they, <hi>calling to remembrance</hi>
               <q>the great jeopardy the Realm standeth in, by the great <hi>conspired malice</hi> of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies environing the same, and every part thereof; <hi>for the Wealth and surety</hi> of the <hi>Realm</hi> inward, and <hi>defence of the same outward,</hi>
               </q> make that Grant: which according to the provision 31 <hi>H.</hi> 6. may be thought a Standing Guard to the King's person; for that was expresly required to be kept together in one entire Body.</p>
            <p>And it seems that anciently Archers used to be in constant pay; for in the <hi>50th</hi> of <hi>E.</hi> 3.<note place="margin">Rot. Parl. <hi>E.</hi> 3. Rot. Parl. 31 <hi>H.</hi> 6. They shall be kept together as one en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Host. Arg. <hi>p.</hi> 16.</note> the Commons having prayed that <hi>Mariners</hi> may have like Wages as <hi>Archers have;</hi> The Answer is, It shall be <hi>as it hath been used.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pray, Gentlemen! Be pleased to look into the Rolls of those Parliaments, and consider how you can reconcile 'em with your random-assertion, that <hi>the few Guards</hi> C. II. kept, <hi>were the first ever known to an English King, besides</hi> his <hi>Pensioners</hi> and <hi>Beef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaters:</hi> And consider what were the 34000 Foot,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:185067:21"/>and 2000 horse under the Command of the Lord <hi>Huns<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> which I formerly mentioned to you, <note place="margin">Vid. Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>p.</hi> 30. Vi d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rg <hi>p.</hi> 25. <hi>p.</hi> 26.</note> that <hi>Q. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> had for the guard of her person: Did she think the hearts of her People enough to secure her <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire?</hi> Or were such as flock'd about her Coach when the Duke of <hi>Alanson</hi> went with her through the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the only <hi>Guard who defended her through a long and successful Reign of</hi> 44 <hi>years, against all the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations of</hi> Rome, <hi>the power of</hi> Spain, &amp;c.?</p>
            <p>Or were the <hi>Militia</hi> all the Soldiers she made use of for the defence of the Kingdom? <note place="margin">1st Letter <hi>p.</hi> 30.</note> when, as I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly observ'd to you, besides the Guard last men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and 20000 placed on the Coasts of <hi>Suffex,</hi> which I take to have been <hi>Militia;</hi> She had an Army of well <hi>disciplined and experienced</hi> men, under the command of the Earl of <hi>Leicester,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting of 1000 Horse, and 22000 Foot, encamped at <hi>Tilbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These, Gentlemen! acted by the Queen's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, and were a <hi>Standing Army</hi> within the very Letter of your <hi>definition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though you were so confident, <note place="margin">Arg <hi>p.</hi> 14. Vid. 1st Letter <hi>p.</hi> 37. Citing <hi>Rushworth</hi> f. 19.427.463. Of Forces, in <hi>Irelond.</hi> Hist. <hi>p.</hi> 3.</note> that if <hi>C.</hi> I. had had 5000 men beforehand with the people, they <hi>had never struck a stroke for their Liberties;</hi> I had before shewn you that he had above 7000 in the Third of his Reign, which were kept in <hi>England</hi> that Winter.</p>
            <p>You admit a necessity of <hi>Standing Armies</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> if we would not lose the <hi>English</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment there; yet you would have it thought, that the <hi>Parliaments</hi> of <hi>England</hi> have been so far from regarding that necessity, that because of the greater danger from or Kings at home, they would not suffer our Kings to <hi>keep up an Army</hi> there: that in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:185067:21"/>the first Three hundred years that the <hi>English</hi> had possession of that Country, there were no Armies, but in the times of War, and that the first Force that was Establish'd, was in the 14th of <hi>E.</hi> 4. by Parliament there.</p>
            <p>At least, one of you, Gentlemen! might have known enough of the place of his Birth, had not his Education been Foreign, to have prevented such gross mistakes concerning it; but certainly it shews an admirable understanding to search for the first Establishment of Forces in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the <hi>Irish</hi> Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Book; and because no Establishment can be found there earlier than 14 <hi>E.</hi> 4. to conclude that the Parliaments of <hi>England</hi> had made no Establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for <hi>Ireland</hi> sooner; and that, notwithstanding the acknowledgment of the <hi>Irish</hi> Parliament, of the <hi>vast and almost infinite expence</hi> of Men, Money, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Irish</hi> Act for Subsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidies. 11 <hi>C.</hi> 1.</note> and Arms, sent out of <hi>England</hi> thither by <hi>C.</hi> I. and his Progenitors.</p>
            <p>Any man that will look into <hi>Cotton</hi>'s Abridgment, if he thinks it not worth his while to see the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Rolls at large, may find numerous instances of Parliamentary Establishments, for Forces in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> before the time you mention; but the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Forces were generally left to the discretion of the Kings and their Councils.</p>
            <p>Thus 5 <hi>E</hi> 3. 'twas fully accorded that the King should pass thither in person; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cotton</hi> Abr. Rot. Parl. 5 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>n.</hi> 4.</note> and that in the mean time <hi>a power be</hi> sent thither, and command be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that all <q>such as have any Lands there, repair thither for defence of the same.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In the next Parliament the King's Expedition was deferr'd for another year, so as <hi>aid might be sent in the mean time.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:185067:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard</hi> the 2 <hi>d</hi> in several Parliaments, <note place="margin">Rot. Parl. 2 R. 2. <hi>N.</hi> 14.24.29.30. 7 R. 2. <hi>n.</hi> 5.14. R. 2. <hi>n.</hi> 1.21 R 2. <hi>n.</hi> 44. and 75. Rot. Parl. 1 <hi>H.</hi> 4. Rot. Parl. 1 <hi>H.</hi> 5. <hi>n.</hi> 9. <hi>Vid.</hi> Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons <hi>Abr.</hi>
               </note> among other charges of the Government, mentions <hi>Ireland;</hi> and the Parliaments here make several Grants, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the occasions. 1 <hi>H.</hi> 4. they give a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidy upon Wooll for 3 years, besides one 10th, and one 15th towards the Wars with <hi>Scotland,</hi> defence of <hi>Calis,</hi> provision for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and amendment of the State.</p>
            <p>And it seems that <hi>Cedules</hi> or Lists used to be given in of the several Establishments; but not being up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Parliament Rolls are not now to be found; 'tis certain that the Parliament Roll 1 <hi>H.</hi> 5. says, <q>the Commons give a <hi>Cedule</hi> for provision to be made touching <hi>Ireland,</hi> the <hi>Marches</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and of <hi>Calice,</hi> touching the <hi>Dutchy</hi> of <hi>Guyenne,</hi> the safe keeping of the Seas, the Navy of <hi>England,</hi> and Governance and due Observance, and for sure provision to be made in Form following.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But no Form is to be found. Indeed certain it is, that generally from the time that <hi>H.</hi> 2. reduced it to a more absolute Subjection to <hi>England,</hi> than any of his Prededessors had done, Soldiers were kept there in constant pay; and when the Revenue of the Crown could not, with the help of <hi>Irish</hi> Parliaments, bear the charge, the Parliaments here have contributed. No man can imagine that <hi>H.</hi> 2. left no <hi>English</hi> Garisons upon his bringing the generality of the Nation under the <hi>English</hi> Laws:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> The History and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of the depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Hoveden f. 324.</note> but besides these the Parliaments of <hi>England</hi> establisht considerable Forces there by Tenures:</p>
            <p>In a Parliament at <hi>Oxford,</hi> that King distributed the Lands of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and their Services; then 'twas that a Grant was made of the County of <hi>Methe</hi> to <hi>Hugh de Lacy,</hi> and his Heirs, as Sir <hi>John Davy</hi>'s has it,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:185067:22"/>to hold by the service of 50 Knight. But <hi>Benedictus Abbas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Davy<hi>'s his Rep. f. 64.</hi> b. M. S. <hi>In Bib. Cot. An. 117 2.</hi> Interea Rex dedit &amp; concessit &amp; cartâ suâ confirmavit Hugoni de Lasci totam terram de Mida cum pertin. suis tenend. in feodo &amp; hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditate de ipso Rege &amp; haered. suis per servitium C. militum &amp; tradidit ei custodiam civitat Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belin.</note> an Author of the Time, makes 'em 100. and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides says the King gave <hi>Lacy</hi> the custody of the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> which being no part of that for which he did his service, had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a sufficient Garison at the charge of the Crown.</p>
            <p>Whereas you will have it, <note place="margin">Hist. f. 9.</note> that our Parliaments <hi>would never suffer our Kings to keep up an Army in</hi> Ireland, <hi>knowing they would be in</hi> England <hi>when call'd for;</hi> This consideration appears to have been one good reason for keeping Forces there. The frequent Wars with the Natives having made their assistance with regular Troops of very great consequence to <hi>England.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cox <hi>s</hi> Hist. of <hi>Ireland.</hi> f. 65. <hi>An.</hi> 1244.</note> Thus in the Time of <hi>H.</hi> 3. success against the <hi>Welsh</hi> was owing to aid from thence.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Edward</hi> the first's time a <hi>smart Party</hi> from thence as the Historian calls 'em, <note place="margin">f. 85. <hi>An.</hi> 1295.</note> did that King good service in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. f. 100. <hi>An.</hi> 1323.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>E.</hi> 2. had from thence in a War against the <hi>Scots</hi> 300 men at Arms, 1000 Hoblers, 6000 Foot, armed with a Seton, a Sallet, and Gloves of Mail, besides 300 supplied by the Earl of <hi>Ʋlster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Still if you please abound in your own sense, <note place="margin">Hist. <hi>p.</hi> 3.</note> That 120 Archers, 40 Horsemen, and 40 Pages, 14 <hi>E.</hi> 4. was the first Force <hi>established</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to that Body of Men which you say <hi>C.</hi> 2. left, I would desire you to reconcile your <hi>History</hi> to your <hi>Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:185067:23"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument,</hi> p. 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Speaking of</hi> C. 2<hi>'s Guards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>He insensibly increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed their Number, till he lest a Body of Men to his Successor, great enough to tell the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, he would be no longer bound by the Laws he had sworn to.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>History,</hi> p. 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Speaking of the D. of</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth<hi>'s Defeat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>King <hi>James</hi> took occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion from hence to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease his Army to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween fifteen and sixteen thousand men, and <hi>then unmask'd himself,</hi> call'd a Parliament, and in an haughty Speech told them he had increas'd his Army, put in Officers not qualified by the Test, and that he would not part with them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The utmost number you make <hi>C.</hi> 2.'s Forces in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd to,<note place="margin">P. 34.</note> is 6950: according to your Argument with these King <hi>James</hi> ventur'd to deal so freely with his Parliament; but now it seems you have better thought of it, he attempted it not without more than twice the number: But you know great Wits have not the best Memories.</p>
            <p>But your Strain of Wit I must confess is admirable, to make the supposed want of opportunities of being rightly inform'd,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Note,</hi> the History makes the Total <hi>24741.</hi> Lord <hi>Rane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagh</hi>'s List but <hi>14834</hi> besides <hi>4</hi> Companies of maimed and decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid Soldiers, <hi>150</hi> in a Company.</note> and the possibility that Officers may recruit, an Argument that you may fairly represent His Majesty's Forces what you please, or as many as if there had been no Reform: Thus you assume a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilege of adding above Nine thousand to the Forces now in <hi>England.</hi> And with the like Fairness you leave about 3000 which had been in Garison at <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gier,</hi> out of the Comparison you make between the Forces of <hi>C.</hi> II. and His present <hi>Majesty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How decently you treat His Majesty, may appear in many Particulars: I may here instance in your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:185067:23"/>after the giving your imaginary number of His Forces.<note place="margin">P. 35. P. 31.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>If, say you, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 37.</note> instead of tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us, That we should be settled upon such a Foundation, that there should be no danger of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into Slavery, and that he would send back all his Forces as soon as that was done; had promis'd us, That after an Eight Years War (which should leave us in Debt near Twenty Millions) we should have a Standing Army establish'd, a great many of which should be Foreigners; I believe few men would have thought such a Revolution worth the hazard of their Lives and Estates.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Whatever is contained in this Reflection, possibly you may help your selves off with your Imagination, that no such thing has yet happen'd, for that there is no Establishment of any Forces; If it be true what you are so warm upon, That there's no other Esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment of any Forces, but a Vote of the House of Commons, to give Money <hi>for Guards and Garisons.</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 25.</note> I wish, Gentlemen, your Heat would have given you time to look into the Act of the last Session of the last Parliament; which in pursuance of that Vote provides <hi>for and towards, the Payment and Satisfaction of such Sum and Sums of Money, as are or shall be due,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Stat.</hi> 9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10 <hi>W.</hi> 3.</note> owing, or payable [for Land and Sea-Services, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd and to be perform'd] and the Charges and Expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces relating thereunto.</p>
            <p>This you may say in your Passion is <hi>what our Courts for above a Thousand Years together had never Effrontery enough to ask:</hi> But,<note place="margin">P. 26.</note> Gentlemen, if after you have considered the Account which I have laid before you of such like Provisions for Land-Forces, you should still maintain the same Opinion, the World will judge on which side the <hi>Effrontery</hi> lies.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:185067:24"/>
            <p>I cannot think that when you have thought again of these matters, you will repeat your Asserti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That the first Footsteps of a Standing Army, that is, according to your own definition, and the description in that very Page, Forces in the King's Pay in time of Peace, were in <hi>R.</hi> H.'s time; and that you <hi>don't find any King from him to</hi> C. I. <hi>that attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed keeping up any Forces in time of Peace, except the Yeomen of the Guard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which is a Mistake much of the same kind with your Assertion, That the <hi>Foreigners</hi> which came over with His Majesty, <hi>is the first Foreign Army</hi> that ever set foot in <hi>England, but as Enemies;</hi> by which you must mean as Enemies to <hi>England,</hi> if you would make any thing of the Reflection: But then what think you of the <hi>Britons</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and of the <hi>Saxons</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards,<note place="margin">Vid. Antiq. Brit. de An. <hi>436.</hi> Pol. Virgil, f. <hi>212.</hi> Ib. f. <hi>559.</hi>
               </note> which came to the relief of the <hi>Britons</hi> here? The 2000 which came over with <hi>E.</hi> 4. against <hi>H.</hi> 6. and the like number with <hi>H.</hi> 7. against <hi>R.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>This leads me to the Pertinency of your History, and Strength of your Reasons; which I may well join in one Head,<note place="margin">Of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency of their Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Strength of their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons.</note> as they illustrate each other, for if the Premises are not to the purpose, your Inferences will fall to the ground; and if you infer not rightly, even where your Premises are the most uncontested, people will be very apt to question their Pertinency to the matter for which you bring 'em.</p>
            <p>Suppose you give a true Account of the Land-For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Old <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>England;</hi> is it not proper to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what was in those Times the Posture of Affairs in relation to the Nations round about? Did any other Land exceed in Numbers of Subjects, and Regularity of Troops? Did it entertain an Abdicated <hi>Prince,</hi> and give him hopes of a powerful assistance for his
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:185067:24"/>Restoration? Were the <hi>Seat of power,</hi> and other places of the greatest Wealth and Resort, left open and almost defenceless, otherwise than with the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of men? Or were there many Castles and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified Towns? If such there were in <hi>England</hi> at the times which you refer to, and are wanting now, when a Neighbouring Prince equals us in Naval, and far over-tops us in Land-Forces, what could be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd from your History, if true,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Hist.</hi> p. 3, 4, 5.</note> with greater Strength or Pertinency, than your fine Satyr upon the Reign of <hi>J.</hi> I.? who by the help of <hi>Toryism,</hi> which then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan its Empire, was Arbitrary without either Courage or Army: which is never wanting to subdue those <hi>Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive Natures,</hi> seiz'd with that vain <hi>Superstition,</hi> which makes Kings as terrible as the like fear does the Pagan Deities. According to your History, through this Superstition <hi>C.</hi> 1. ventured upon all those <hi>Oppressions</hi> of his Reign, which as you say 'twere <hi>endless to enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merate:</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 6.</note> But you know his Tyranny was <hi>precarious,</hi> because he had <hi>no Army to support him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The several Mutations which you pathetically de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe in the time when your <hi>Ʋtopian</hi> State began, certainly yield a stronger Argument of the Vanity of such Projects,<note place="margin">P. 1.</note> than of a <hi>Standing Army</hi>'s being <hi>Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very,</hi> Popery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then the Nation could not but be in a perpetual Agitation, and a small Accession of Strength to either of the contending Parties, must needs turn the uncertain Scale, till it came to its Center of <hi>Monarchy.</hi> In King <hi>Charles</hi> II. you shew an Arbitrary Disposition, and love to Popery; and that he was possessed of an Army of 12000 men,<note place="margin">P. 13.</note> which <hi>were encamped upon</hi> Black-Heath, <hi>and hovering over the City of</hi> London; yet 'tis your own confessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that these <hi>put both the Parliament and City in such confusion, that he was forc'd to disband them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:185067:25"/>
            <p>How came it to pass, that if <hi>C.</hi> I. had had but 5000 <hi>before-hand with us, the Nation could not have struck one stroke for their Liberties;</hi> and yet this Nation forc'd <hi>C.</hi> II. to disband 12000, tho at the same time he had 10000 <hi>more in the</hi> French <hi>Service,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 14.</note>
               <hi>for the most part under Popish Officers?</hi> Would all those, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the Lord <hi>Dunbarton,</hi> have been as generous as <hi>General Schomberg,</hi> in scorning to <hi>put Chains upon a Free People?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s Misfortune was to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to many Causes; however, the Success of the <hi>Regular Troops</hi> against his Numbers, which all must agree to have been as good as the <hi>Militia,</hi> and headed by an extraordinary <hi>General;</hi> leaves a <hi>sad Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect</hi> of the consequence of an Invasion, when there are no <hi>Regular Troops</hi> to make a Stand, and head the <hi>Militia,</hi> or others, that should draw together from all parts.</p>
            <p>But tho the <hi>late King</hi> was flush'd with Success, and had made a great addition to his Armies; the Recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which His <hi>present Majesty</hi> had, without oppositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, shews that a great Army cannot establish <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> in <hi>England:</hi> And yet the very few that came in to His <hi>present Majesty,</hi> or were in any Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Preparation in the <hi>North,</hi> tho he gave 'em Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement and Opportunity, may leave it a question, Whether a <hi>Foreign Popish Army</hi> would be likely to meet with considerable opposition from one of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Person's <hi>Millions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. Confut. of the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancing Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>p. 12.</hi>
               </note> who if it could be Mr. <hi>J</hi>—<hi>n,</hi> so eminent for his Zeal and Sufferings against Popery, and those <hi>Doctrines of the Bow-string,</hi> which would introduce that, or <hi>Mahometism,</hi> much more easily than an Army of 40000 <hi>Protestants</hi> can possibly do; I cannot but say 'twere an unhappy Evidence,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:185067:25"/>that the greatest Minds may at some times be clouded.</p>
            <p>But since that Writer's Fears lye wholly the same way with yours, 'tis natural to think that his Hopes do too; and therefore I may be allowed to treat his envenom'd Dart as taken from your Quiver, and dipt in the same Poyson.</p>
            <p>Upon his State of the Question,<note place="margin">P. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Whether the Militia as 'tis at present, and the whole Strength of <hi>England</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, is sufficient to oppose an Invasion, without a Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Army? he supposes, 1. That tho there should be no force together, 'twere easy to form an Army of the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded Soldiers and others, and to put them in order time enough to resist any Invasion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all men will be united in this.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That upon an Invasion, we have 20000 ready enough to entertain an Enemy,<note place="margin">P. 11.</note> tho they do not stand regimental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together; and we have 30000 as well finish'd Soldiers as they; and an hundred and fifty thousand more, that either are, or soon may be, as good as either of them; and some Millions of Able Men, who when they are tried, may behave themselves as well as any of them all.<note place="margin">P. 21.</note> Nay, he grows upon it, and afterwards says, In Seven Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we have so great choice, that if One Million will not fight to defend their Native Country, Another will, and a Third may see fair Play, and a Fourth is a good Reserve, and so are all the rest.</p>
            <p>But if Mr. <hi>J</hi>—<hi>n</hi> be the Author of that Book, as he sadly experimented how far a sort of People are from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing True <hi>Englishmen;</hi> whether the Dread of Foreign Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry will unite them that contributed to it at home; and whether his Supposition here agrees with his Notion, That all Strangers within this Land are to be look'd on as Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; and that there's an <hi>Englishman</hi> the less for every one of them; I must recommend to his unclouded Thoughts. And I would desire him to consider, whether the Instances are frequent, of Nations, how Populous so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, that have drawn several Armies into the Field one
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:185067:26"/>after another, notwithstanding the Defeat of their best Troops, on which they chiefly depended.</p>
            <p>And I would gladly know, whether 'tis reasoning like Mr. <hi>J</hi>—<hi>n,</hi> to say,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The new Trust the Letter</hi> (he pretends to confute) <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists upon, is an Army which can over-power and conquer the Nation:</hi> For it is to be such a <hi>Force as can withstand an Invasion which all the Nation besides is not able to do; that is to say, it can beat those that can beat us, and therefore it can much more beat us.</hi> I would desire him but to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his own State of the Question in relation to the <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> and apply it to such Forces as the Parliament should think fit to continue. This would have moderated his Censures of them who are for some Regular Forces, as if they endeavour <hi>to alter tyhe Government at once: go about to Arm the King against the Constitution;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pref. P. 9. P. 16.</note> put a Trust in the King which no man <hi>can deserve;</hi> are for <hi>such an abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Resignation,</hi> as is only <hi>proper to be made to God;</hi> and for the establishing such a Force <hi>as is an actual Surrender of all our Liberties at once,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and would make us as effectual Slaves as a Conquest can make us.</hi> All these flights of Fancy are grounded upon a manifest begging the question; and some will think are heightned with not a few Grains of Prejudice, against the Person who is taken for the Author of that Letter.</p>
            <p>Something for certain is the cause that makes the whole frame of this Book widely to differ from Mr. <hi>J.</hi> in Reasoning, tho it resembles his Stile: Thus the Author would infer that a King of <hi>England</hi> has not absolute Power, because he was empowered by the <hi>Folcmote;</hi> by the same way of arguing he might conclude that the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperors were not absolute, because as the <hi>Lex Regia</hi> has it, <hi>the people conferr'd all their Power upon 'em:</hi> But 'tis not the Gift as such, but the degree and manner of it, which makes the Power absolute or limited; and therefore we say a K. of <hi>England</hi> is not absolute, because the People have not made
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:185067:26"/>such a Resignation of themselves as the <hi>Romans</hi> did to the <hi>Caesars,</hi> or particularly to <hi>Augustus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you, Gentlemen, know how to comfort him with the assurance, that his Arguments are never the weaker,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Milit. ref.</hi> p. 67.</note> for the justest Objections; according to that Noble Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, <hi>My Assertions are not the less solid, because some people are Cowards, and others now unaccustomed to what their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stors successfully practis'd heretofore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Great Wits can reconcile all differences in Persons, Times, and other Circumstances; make Conwards valiant, and discipline their Militia in a moment, to equal Troops the most inured to War; and inspire their Principles of Liberty into the <hi>Bigots</hi> for the <hi>Divine Right,</hi> of the next in the Royal Line, to a Power which the People neither gave, nor can limit or qualify.</p>
            <p>I am not in the least surpriz'd to find you, Gentlemen, confound Things and Persons, made <hi>Tories</hi> of <hi>Whigs,</hi> and <hi>Whigs</hi> of <hi>Tories;</hi> any more than I am to find that Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate for unbounded Liberty, Mr. <hi>J. T.</hi> with decent regard to an Act of Parliament,<note place="margin">Life of <hi>J. Milton,</hi> p. 77, 78. By reason of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians warmly joining with others the last Parliament to promote Penal Laws against the <hi>Socinians,</hi> I find few people will believe that those in <hi>England</hi> differ from their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>Scotland</hi> about persecution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> P. 79. <hi>After ridiculing the Project of a Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension.</hi> — the Wishes of all good men are, that the National Church being secured in her Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and Emoluments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> to charge the Presbyterians with being accessary to Persecution, in joining with others the last Parliament, to promote Penal Laws against those that deny the Mysteries of Christianity: nor do I wonder at his mighty concern for <hi>High Church,</hi> lest by a prudent Comprehension the Profits should be divided, and the Protestant Interest strengthned and united under King <hi>William.</hi> When he pretends to express the Wishes of all <hi>Good Men</hi> against a Comprehension, and for the National Church establish'd by Law to engross the Profits; he leaves it a question, Whether <hi>Socinianism,</hi> whose Suppression he dreads, is not dearer to him even than a <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> which he with all his Art can never propose to set up on so narrow a bottom. However, 'tis evident Mr. <hi>Harring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> never did; whose <hi>Oceana,</hi> or <hi>Agrarian,</hi> and new jumbling
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:185067:27"/>of Property,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Life of</hi> M p. 122.</note> Mr. <hi>J. T.</hi> recommends as the <hi>most perfect</hi> Form of a Commonwealth, for <hi>the Practicableness, Equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and Compleatness of it, that ever was delineated by any Ancient or Modern Pen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But should Mr. <hi>J</hi>—<hi>n</hi>'s Fears lye all one way, against nothing but the Power of King <hi>William;</hi> should he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get from whence the Barbarities inflicted upon him came, and whence his Deliverance; how far <hi>Church Bigottry</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to the Ruin of the Constitution, and how 'twas preserv'd by a Foreign Force; would not some impute his new Fears to a turning of his Brain; especially when they come to observe how grosly he, if he writ the pretended Confutation, mistakes the Authorities which he urges against a General Act of Naturalization, and the admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Strangers among us?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of their Mistakes concerning the Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Monarchy.</note>It has sufficiently appear'd above, and might more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that your Reflections upon the Ministry for their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to have a sufficient <hi>Land Force,</hi> under Parliamentary Regulations and Establishment, are grounded upon gross mistakes of the Constitution, as it relates to Soldiery. Nor will you be found more knowing in other Branches of it.</p>
            <p>According to your exact knowledge of all its Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,<note place="margin">Pref. to the Hist. <hi>p. 4.</hi>
               </note> from the time that the <hi>Romans</hi> quitted this Isle, you affirm, that <hi>the Places in the King's Gift were but few, and most of them Patent-Places for Life:</hi> To enhance the Charge against the Court for making more Places than us'd to be, you bring in the Commissioners for Hackney-Coaches, and other Officers,<note place="margin">P. 5.</note> whose Numbers are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Act of Parliament; and therefore must needs be held to have been without any breach of the Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: As to others 'twill be very difficult to shew that there are more now in the King's Gift, than this Predeces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ssors used to have. Certain 'tis, 1. that there were many Offices which are wholly discontinued, or not in the Crown, because of the alienation of those Hundreds, Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liwicks, Mannors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> on which they depend; and others,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:185067:27"/>which tho kept up in Name, have very insignificant Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laries or Perquisites; for which I chuse to instance in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Offices, such as the Government of Castles and Towns formerly fortified. 2. Many of your Friends now enjoy Offices either during Life, or as long as they behave themselves well; some of which according to ancient Custom, were to be only during pleasure; and others are void, as being held by colour of <hi>non obstante</hi>'s to Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes: Of which I can, when occasion requires, shew great numbers.</p>
            <p>Therefore I may conclude, that according to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution, the King and the Court ought to have the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposal of more Offices, than they now take upon them to dispose of.</p>
            <p>Again, you say,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pref.</hi> p. 7.</note>
               <hi>Our Government trusts the King with no part of the Legislative, but a Negative Voice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereby you would take from the King the liberty to propose; which, if you consult the Rolls of Parliament, and other Records, you will find to have been the undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Right of the Crown; and indeed it might with as much colour be said, that anciently the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons us'd only a Negative, when the Bills were proposed ready drawn by the King's Council: But 'tis past dispute that either proposed to the other, as there was occasion.</p>
            <p>Then you affirm with great assurance,<note place="margin">Ʋsd. Rot. Parl. de <hi>1</hi> H. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>formerly</hi> all <q>matters of state and discretion were debated and resolv'd in the Privy-Council, where every man subscrib'd his Opinion, and was answerable for it: And that the Late King <hi>Charles</hi> was the first who broke this most excellent part of our Constitution, by setling a Cabal or <hi>Cabinet Council.</hi>
               </q> Whereas,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The substance of the Cabinet Council has been very ancient, and that allowed of by Parliament, as appears by their settling a <hi>Quorum</hi> of persons most confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in, without whose presence no arduous matter was to be determined; and yet they had power to act with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out consulting the rest of the Council.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:185067:28"/>
            <p>Thus as long since as the 28th of <hi>H.</hi> 3. a Charter pass'd,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Mat. Par. 28</hi> H. <hi>3.</hi> De communi assensu qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuoreligan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur potentes &amp; nobiles.</note> in affirmance of the Ancient Right of the<note n="b" place="margin">Et erunt libertatum Conservato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</note> Kingdom, which provided that 4 great Men chosen by <hi>common assent,</hi> who were to be Conservators of the Kingdom, among other things should<note n="c" place="margin">Per visum &amp; testimonium eorum tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctetur The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saurus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Regis &amp; pecunia ab universis specialiter concessa ad commodum domini Regis &amp; Regni expendatur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> see to the disposing of the Monies given by Parliament, and appropriated to particular uses; and<note n="d" place="margin">Nec sine ipsis sed cum necesse fuerit &amp; ad eorum instantism iterum conveniant universi</note> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were to be summon'd as they should advise. But even of<note n="e" place="margin">Et si non omnes duo ad minus present es sint, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> these four any two made a <hi>Quorum;</hi> and<note n="f" place="margin">Et quia frequenter debent esse cum duo Rege poterunt esse de numero Conservatorum.</note> generally the Chief Justice of <hi>England,</hi> and Chancellor were of the number of the Conservators, or in the Modern Language, of the <hi>Cabinet Council.</hi> Not particularly to observe the resemblances to this in the Ages downwards; In the<note n="g" place="margin">Rot. Parl. 1. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 30. <hi>n.</hi> 31</note> first of <hi>H.</hi> 6. the Parliament provides that the <hi>Quorum</hi> for the Privy <hi>Council</hi> be 6 or 4 at the least; and that in all weighty Consultations the <hi>Dukes</hi> of <hi>Bedford</hi> and <hi>Gloster,</hi> the King's Uncles, should be present.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Twill be difficult for you to find the least footsteps of any Constitution, requiring the <hi>Council</hi> to subscribe their Opinions. Indeed as early as 1 <hi>H.</hi> 6. there's a provision suita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the practice at this day, for the <hi>Clerk</hi> of the <hi>Council</hi> to enter,<note place="margin">Rot. Parl. 1 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>n.</hi> 31.</note> who was present from time to time, that it might be seen, as the Roll has it, <hi>what Law, and by whom any thing passeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since this is done at this day, this reflection vanishes th] with the rest of like grounds; nor will your Friend the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the suppos'd <hi>Confutation,</hi> appear either to know the Constitution better,<note place="margin">Of Foreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>p. 25.</hi>
               </note> or to represent it more fairly, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to <hi>Foreigners,</hi> he says indeed, <q>That the Wisdom of the Nation in former Ages, by which we subsist at this day, was against the admitting any Aliens into the Kingdom, unless it were Merchants for the sake of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and they too were restrain'd in these two points, besides divers others, not to take an House, nor stay above
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:185067:28"/>40 days, as we find by the <hi>London</hi> Petition, reciting the Ancient Usages, and the Act made upon it 5 <hi>E.</hi> 3.</q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis but just that he who would render his Native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try so inhospitable, should stumble at the Threshold;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rot. Parl. 50.</hi> E. <hi>3.</hi> De fair leur de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meure ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre <hi>40.</hi> jours la. Resp. Deins la dict, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Both the Petition and Answer relate only to the City of <hi>London,</hi> and its Suburbs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Answer even in relation to <hi>London,</hi> excepts some Foreigners, <hi>saving to the Merchants of the Hanse of</hi> Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, the <hi>Franchises</hi> granted them, and <hi>confirm'd</hi> by <hi>E.</hi> 3 <hi>ds Progenitors.</hi> Whether this be an honest Quotation, or rightly understood by this Celebrated Author, I leave you to judge.</p>
            <p>Indeed he might have cited the <hi>Mirror</hi> with better co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour;<note place="margin">Mirror. <hi>c. 1. Sect. 3.</hi>
               </note> Defendus fuistquaenul Merchant alien, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which speaking of Laws made by King <hi>Alfred,</hi> and following Kings says, <q>All Merchant Aliens were forbid to frequent <hi>England,</hi> except at 4 Fairs; nor were nay them to stay in the Land above 40 days.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This at first sight looks like an Authority his way; but take it with the <hi>Mirrors</hi> Explanation, and 'twill appear that no man was to continue an Alien 40 days; but if he staid so long, was to take the Oath of Allegiance,<note place="margin">Mirror. <hi>p. 283. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>busion.</hi> b. Anglois eu alien. Sil ne soit jure al Roy per sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment de fealty &amp; plevise &amp; en dasiene▪</note> and from that time he became a Liege and Natural Subject; for the <hi>Mirror</hi> among the abusions of the Law, reckons it one, <q>That any one above the Age of 14 years, whether <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish or Alien,</hi> should be suffer'd to stay in the Realm, <hi>if he be not sworn to the King,</hi> by Oath of Fealty, and Frank pledge, and in a Tithing.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This shews that in the Eye of the Law they are the true Aliens, and out of the King's Protection, who will not Swear Allegiance to him.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Mirror</hi> shews how mistaken this Confuter was, in urging the Law of Frank pledges, to prove that in such a Constitution <q>'twas impossible for a stranger to thrust in his <hi>Nose.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cnof <hi>p.</hi> 26.</note>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>As 'twas not impossible for Foreigner s tobe known to their Correspondents here, and to be confederated with
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:185067:29"/>them by mutual Oaths,<note place="margin">Leges Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuti c. <hi>52.</hi> Habeat omnis do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliam suam in plegio suo. Vid Leges Alured: c. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> for the defence of the King and Kingdom; 'twas far from being impossible, that <hi>English</hi> men should be bound for the good behaviour of such Strangers: and then Merchants and other Strangers of Quality, might retain many with them in their Families, by virtue of the Law, which made every <hi>Master of a Family</hi> the <hi>Pledge,</hi> or Sponsor for his own <hi>Family.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Coram prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posito Regio in frequenti populi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventu. Quae ex aequo jure coacta populi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cione quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sita fuerint.</note>And I would desire you, or the <hi>Confuter,</hi> to tell me your sense of King <hi>Alfred</hi>'s Law about Merchants, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides, <q>That Merchants carry before the King's Officer in <hi>a full Convention of the people,</hi> those whom they bring to Land with them out of the Ship; and shew their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and then they may retain them with them, to have them ready to answer all those things which shall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <hi>according to Law,</hi> in the <hi>Assembly of the People.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This I take to relate to the monthly Assembly of the People at the County Court, or the usual Court day in any City or Town where they arrived: and according to the Explanation of this which we may take from the Mirror, they were to be demanded whether they would take the Oath of Allegiance, or depart the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Farther yet, to shew how the Notion of <hi>Aliens</hi> is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staken, it seems a great Question, whether in the Eye of the Law, from within the Time of King <hi>John,</hi> to the making the Statute <hi>De Prerogativa Regis,</hi> any were <hi>truly Aliens,</hi> but such as were of the <hi>Allegiance of the King</hi> of <hi>France, and had not sworn Allegiance to the King of</hi> England.<note place="margin">Vid. Graft. Ann. <hi>1206.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> having wrested <hi>Normandy</hi> out of the hands of the <hi>English.</hi> 7 of <hi>King John,</hi> then, or some short time after, a Law was made, which by way of Reprisal, Vested in the Crown of this Realm, the Lands which the <hi>Normans</hi> had here: which were <hi>called the Escheats of the</hi> Normans.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:185067:29"/>
            <p>Thus I find <hi>Breweton</hi> said to be of the Lands of the <hi>Normans,</hi> and Granted out by King <hi>John,</hi> and the Manour of <hi>Warblinton,</hi> said to be the Kings <hi>Escheat,</hi> as being Land belonging to <hi>Normans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Statute supposed to be made, 17. <hi>E.</hi> 2. tho' I take it to have been made in 17. <hi>E.</hi> 1. declaring the Kings <hi>Prerogative</hi> in some particulars, says, the <q>King shall have the <hi>Escheat</hi> of the Lands of <hi>Normans,</hi> of whose Fee soever they be. <hi>It adds</hi> so 'tis to be understood, <hi>If any Inheritance Descend to any born in Forein Parts, and whose Ancestors were of the Allegiance of the King of</hi> France, <hi>from the time of King</hi> John, <hi>and not of the Allegiance of the King of</hi> England.</q>
            </p>
            <p>By this it seems there might be a Double <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance;</hi> and he who had been born in <hi>France</hi> and swore to that King, might, by Residing and Swearing Allegiance here, <hi>cease to be an Alien,</hi> within the meaning of that Law. And<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bracton lib.</hi> 5. De Exceptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne quia alienigena.</note>
               <hi>Bracton,</hi> who writ in the Reign of <hi>H.</hi> 3. Treating of the Exception, <hi>because an Alien,</hi> says, <q>there are those that are of the Allegiance of <hi>both Kings,</hi> as <hi>William Earl Marshal,</hi> Residing in <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Michael de Seins</hi> Residing in <hi>France,</hi> and others.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But it seems by <hi>Bracton,</hi> that in his time, they who were only of the Allegiance of the King of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bracton</hi> ib. Talis non ris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, saltem donec ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae sint commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> might recover <hi>Lands and Tenements,</hi> in an Action at Law, when there was Peace between the two Kingdoms: Tho' till the Statute <hi>De nat is ultra mare</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Stat. 25. <hi>E.</hi> 3.</note>, which allows of the Certificate of a <hi>French</hi> Bishop to prove Legitimation; the Son of an <hi>English</hi>-man, born when his Father were abroad, even upon Merchandizing, or in an Ambassadors House, could not be proved Heir in a real Action, for<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Test. de</hi> Nevil <hi>temp. E.</hi> 1. In sccio De Escha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etis, de Terris Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Eschaeta dni Regis sicut Terra Normanno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:185067:30"/>want of such a Certificate as our Law could take notice of; yet I take it to be beyond question, that all <hi>Aliens</hi> residing in <hi>England,</hi> and qualifying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves by the Oath requir'd of Resyants, if they who were not of the <hi>Allegiance of the King of France,</hi> might Purchase Lands in <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leton</hi> Sect. 198.</note> which should descend to their Heirs, till at least the 17th. of <hi>E.</hi> 1. By <hi>Littletons</hi> time, who Writ in the Reign of <hi>E.</hi> 4. the Law was taken to reach farther against men Born beyond Sea than before, for by that time, all who were born <hi>out of the King</hi>'s <hi>Allegiance</hi> were counted <hi>Aliens,</hi> not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting those whose Fathers and Mothers, are <hi>English:</hi> contrary to the opinion of the Learned Judge <hi>Hussey</hi> in the time of <hi>R.</hi> 3. who held,<note place="margin">1 <hi>R.</hi> 3. f. 4.</note> that by the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law,</hi> and <hi>especially by the Statute,</hi> such are <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the General Opinion now being otherwise, many of <hi>English</hi> Parents have had recourse to Acts of <hi>Naturalization,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of Acts of Naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation, and Natural born Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</note> the Forms of some of which only declare them <hi>Liege and Natural Subjects;</hi> which possibly is not thought of by some, who would not only Exclude Foreiners, but many of the Kings <hi>Natural Subjects</hi> of <hi>English</hi> Parents, from the Priviledges of <hi>English</hi> Men: not thinking of Sir <hi>William Temples</hi> Maxim,<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Will. Temples</hi> Miscella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. p. 23.</note> that a good Government ought to resemble a <hi>Pyramid</hi> with as large a Basis as may be.</p>
            <p>But a <hi>General Act of Naturalization,</hi> the <hi>Confuter</hi>
               <q>says is, 'a Project so contrary to our Constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he who has the Original <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> with King <hi>John</hi>'s Seal to it, may find there, if he pleases to look into it, <hi>this Original English Right,</hi> that all Strangers shall be amoved out of the Kingdom,</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:185067:30"/>
            <p>To me, who had not only seen Prints of <hi>King</hi> John's <hi>Charter,</hi> but examined as diligently as I could, that in the <hi>Cotton Library,</hi> (which is no less an <hi>Original,</hi> for not now having the King's Seal to it) this Assertion seem'd very strange; especially finding there these Clauses.</p>
            <p n="50">
               <note place="margin">Vid. Dr. <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy's</hi> Append. to his comp. 0199 0235 V 2 History upon comparing <hi>Mat. Par.</hi> with the Hist in <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> Colledge Library.</note>50. <q>Let <hi>all Merchants,</hi> unless such as are pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly 01 Prohibited, be safe and secure to go <hi>out of England,</hi> and <hi>come into England,</hi> and <hi>to go as well by Land as by Water,</hi> to Buy or Sell, without any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of evil Tolls, according to the <hi>ancient</hi> and <hi>right Customs: Ʋnless in time of War,</hi> and that they be of a Land in a War against us.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="51">
               <note place="margin">Omnes Mercatores nisi Publice prohibiti 0199 0235 V 2 fuerint ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant salv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum exire de Angl. &amp; venire in Angl. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>51. <q>And if such are found in our Land, at the beginning of a War, let them be attach'd <hi>without 01 damage</hi> of their bodies or Goods, till it be known by <hi>us</hi> or our <hi>Chief Justice,</hi> how the <hi>Merchants</hi> of our Land are treated in the Land at War against us: And if ours are safe there, <hi>let others be safe in England.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="52">52. <q>Be it Lawful <hi>for every one</hi> henceforth, to go out of our Kingdom, and <hi>come back</hi> safely and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely by <hi>Land</hi> and by <hi>Water; care being taken of our allegiance:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Salva fide nostra.</note> Unless in time of War <hi>for some short time,</hi> by reason of the <hi>publick Good</hi> of the Kingdom: Except Persons <hi>Imprison'd and Outlaw'd,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Propter commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemutilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem regni.</note>
                  <hi>according to the Law of the Kingdom,</hi> and People in War a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us, and <hi>Merchants;</hi> concerning whom, let it be done as is abovesaid.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This is a manifest Invitation to other <hi>Foreigners</hi> besides <hi>Merchants,</hi> if either they would swear <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance,</hi> according to what the <hi>Mirror</hi> shews to have been required of all, who would stay here above 40
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:185067:31"/>Days, or at least would not give reasonable grounds to apprehend their endangering the Kings Peace.</p>
            <p>To imagin,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Confutation Pag.</hi> 30.</note> therefore, that all Strangers were by <hi>King</hi> John's <hi>Charter</hi> to be <hi>amoved</hi> out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, were to suppose it contradictory and inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stent with it self.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Articuli magnae chartae sub sigillo Reg. <hi>Joh.</hi> penes doctissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Epm Salisb. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. 6 quod Rex amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veret mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes stipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diarios &amp; alios qui venerunt cum equis, &amp; armis ad nocumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum regni.</note>But this wonderful <hi>Confuter,</hi> not only mistakes Preliminary Articles Signed before the <hi>great Charter,</hi> for the Charter it self; but either mistakes or disin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuously represents that Preliminary Article which relates to <hi>Foreigners,</hi> which was, that the King should amove Foreign Mercenary Soldiers and others, who came <hi>with Horses and Arms for the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage or destruction of the Realm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to make all <hi>Foreigners</hi> within the provision against those, who came over <hi>in Arms against the Kingdom,</hi> I take, <hi>Gentlemen</hi> to be by one of your usual Figures.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Confuter,</hi> supposing this to take in all Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, says,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Confut. Pag.</hi> 23.</note>
               <q>Accordingly the practice was ever, both before and since, <hi>to keep Strangers out of the Kingdom;</hi> or when ever they got in, and encreas'd to any number, <hi>to expel them, and set them a fatal Day for their departure: By which time they all shrunk away and vanished, like so many Phantasms or Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions:</hi> For so the Old Historians pleasantly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press it.</q> Which is not only to bring all <hi>Foreigners</hi> into what related to such only as had been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of; but to apply to <hi>King</hi> John's <hi>Charter,</hi> and the consequent upon that, what upon Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, will appear to have been spoken of the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the Third, or some other Prince, who gave just Jealousy to his People: This indeed King <hi>John</hi> had done, but he was so
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:185067:31"/>far from amoving all dangerous <hi>Foreigners,</hi> after the signing those Articles, that he used the assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of many of 'em who continued in <hi>England</hi> from before that time,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Annales waverlenses f. <hi>181.</hi> de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no <hi>1215.</hi> Rege verò è contra per alienige nos &amp; alios sibi adhaerentes saevissimè de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacchante multiplicate sunt mala, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim applicuerunt in Angliam alienigenae bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bari &amp; magna multitudo diversar. lingua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, errorem Regis pertinaciter confoventes.</note> and had others who came over af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, to support the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olations of his <hi>Great Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As a right Line exposes the obliquity of the Crooked, I need not give the Quotations as they are used in that Book, their due Character: but they have so little of Mr. <hi>J—n</hi>'s Judgment or Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, and relish so much of your judicious and fair way of representing Persons and things; that your obtruding upon the World, that inconsiderate Rant as Mr. <hi>J—n</hi>'s, seems to me a <hi>Master-piece</hi> of your Politicks, next to your colouring a Project for inciting the <hi>French King</hi> to break the Peace, by laying <hi>England</hi> open to his Arms, with a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Zeal for the Constitution and Liberties of your Country.</p>
            <p>I wonder not to find the old Game revived, which in the late times was plaid with success, by Sir <hi>Job Charlton</hi> and others, who cover'd their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs for bringing in <hi>C.</hi> the II. with appearing mighty zealous for a <hi>Commonweath.</hi> But to examine the Truth of your pretended Zeal for the Liberties of your Country, or the knowledge which accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies it, 'twill be requisite to take a short View of your Means for securing those Blessings which you would be thought the most concerned for.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Confuter,</hi> who would have all Foreigners of whatever Religion, and how much soever they
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:185067:32"/>have signaliz'd themselves, in the Service of his Majesty and this Nation, to be reputed <hi>Enemies,</hi> thinks one great Point for securing the Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were to Banish all Foreigners.</p>
            <p>With him there's no danger from Men of <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Allegiance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">pag. 147.</note> tho' it be Popery; which, as <hi>J. T.</hi> has licence to observe from Mr. <hi>Milton, is intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, not as 'tis a Religion, but as a Tyrannical Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, oppressing all others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>Constitution</hi> do's not require the depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Foreigners,</hi> has appeared above: The true Argument against 'em is <hi>Toryism</hi> at the bottom; which is, That they are not to be supposed so zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for preserving to the <hi>National Church, her Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and Emoluments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Life of</hi> Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, p. 79.</note> as Mr. <hi>J. T.</hi> expresses himself, in complaisance to his New Friends.</p>
            <p>But Foreigners united with us, in the common Interest of all Protestants, and the mutual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federation of Oaths, to <hi>defend the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> by all indifferent persons must be held to bring additional Strength and Riches to the Nation: espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if careful provision be made, that the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallity of 'em, be well employ'd in Agriculture, Manufactures, or working in Mines; whereby an immense Treasure might be added to the Nation, and the Ballance of Trade so turned on our side, that we should fetch Money from every Nation with which we dealt: the Advantages of which are frequently observed by the Author of the <hi>Essay upon probable Methods of making a People Gainers in the Ballance of Trade.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Essay,</hi> p. 24, 25, 27, 28, 36, 50, 78, 99.</note> To which I may add, That whatever encrease of People any Nation has from its own stock, is for several Years an addition to the Charge; as the Children must be maintain'd by the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:185067:32"/>labour of others; whereas Strangers, for the most part, come over adult, in a capacity to add to the Wealth of the Nation: And if they occasion Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships to any of our Artificers, by their cheap way of living, the more they enrich the Kingdom, and prevent our Trading abroad, for those things with which they supply us at home. 'Tis well known, That our most advantageous Manufactures have been brought hither, or improved, by Foreigners, whose descendents are become as true English Men, as even your selves; and that the <hi>French Refingees</hi> setled in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> have vastly diminished the Trade of <hi>Lyons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Confutation,</hi> p. 28, 29.</note> and serve for a much better pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose than <hi>to make a dearth of Provisions:</hi> If <hi>their passive and slavish Principles were of great use to</hi> C. II. <hi>and very instructive to his own People how to bear all the Hostilities of their Prince;</hi> certainly they fell very short of those Tools to Arbitrary Power which you caress, as the chief <hi>Patriots,</hi> next to your selves. Nor must it be forgoten, that but for the Treachery of your Friends and assistance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the brave <hi>Rochellers,</hi> the <hi>French Hugonots</hi> had to this day continued Examples of Christian For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, in opposing that Antichristian Tyranny, which they cannot be said to have submitted to of choice, as your dear Friends have done.</p>
            <p>But what ever Objection you may have against the <hi>French;</hi> methinks you should not apprehend any Accession to Absolute Monarchy from the setling here of <hi>Dutchmen,</hi> whose Arms threw off the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> Yoak, with disadvantages insuperable, but for the Courage and Conduct of the <hi>Orange Family,</hi> who have been raised up for <hi>Deliverers</hi> of oppressed nations.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:185067:33"/>
            <p>Since all unprejudiced Persons must agree, that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious Foreiners, United in the same Sacred and Civil Interest, and Oaths for mutual Preservation and Support of the Government, are to be looked on as Strength and Riches, to a Nation; That which is most likely to encourage such to settle here, must needs be a probable means to Strengthen and Enrich <hi>England.</hi> Since therefore, (without an Act of <hi>Naturalization,</hi> general to all who will come under fit Qualifications,) as the Law now stands, or is taken, they cannot have the Prive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Englishmen,</hi> without such a Charge, as none but the Wealthy and least Industrious can bear; to me it seems that an Act of <hi>Naturali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation,</hi> with due provisions for their Renouncing <hi>Forein</hi> both <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Allegiance,</hi> would be greatly for the Publick good.</p>
            <p>But since the <hi>Confuter</hi> supposes all <hi>Foreiners</hi> of whatever <hi>Religion</hi> or Country, to be Enemies, and that every one of 'em ought to have an <hi>Englishman</hi> to Guard or engage, him upon an Invasion; and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience tells us, that all Papists, tho' Natives, and all that refuse the Oaths to this Government, are at least equally dangerous with <hi>Protestant Aliens;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides which, there are a loose and desperate sort of People disposed to fall in with any Power that may give 'em hopes of a Change; and others, who expect upon an Confusion, to have a new Forming of the Government, according to the beloved <hi>Agrarian</hi> Model; how many of the <hi>Confuters</hi> Millions can be thought likely to oppose an Invasion? especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if it be considered, that a Person more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act in his Computation, holds, that the number of <hi>Fighting-Men</hi> between 16 and 60, is but
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:185067:33"/>
               <hi>One Million,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Essay</hi> p. 22.</note>
               <hi>Three Hundred</hi> and <hi>Eighty Thousand</hi> Men.</p>
            <p>They who argue so warmely against all Regular Forces, and so much value the numbers which would be drawn together to oppose a <hi>Forein Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion,</hi> would do well not only to consider how many were ready to joyn that Power, which came to Rescue 'em from as certain ruin, but to recollect the passages of the doughty Adventure at that time, against the Boughs and Bodies of Trees, which the shades of approaching night and horror, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Represented as so many Armed Men, did more mischief than <hi>Don Quixot</hi>'s <hi>Wind-Mill;</hi> when the <hi>Posse</hi> of several Counties; the <hi>Gentry,</hi> with their Servants and Followers, taking a false A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm, without thinking to send out <hi>Scouts,</hi> or to consult any thing but their panick fears, left their Baggage and Portmanteaus behind 'em in their Flight; and verified of Wealthy Soldiers, what the <hi>Satyrist</hi> says of a Man that Travels by night with a Charge of Money,</p>
            <q>Motaeque ad Lunam trepidabit arundinis umbram.</q>
            <p>Tho the Living <hi>Heroes</hi> may not be very fond of having their Names Recorded to Posterity, for this Adventure; That it may be no question what time I speak of, 'twas when Mr. <hi>Wren Bray</hi>'s fright, or the immediate Consequence of it, hastened his End.</p>
            <p>To come to the particular means proposed by you Gentlemen of the <hi>Rota,</hi> for the securing this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and it's Liberties; sometimes you Insinuate that we have need of nothing but a good <hi>Naval pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision:</hi> Thus in one of your <hi>Rhapsodies,</hi> very differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:185067:34"/>that from that <hi>leanness of Thought,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Letter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Guards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. <hi>2.</hi> Argument p. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>and flatness of Expression,</hi> which you charge upon all that call your Oracles in question; you say, <hi>These Halcyon days we enjoy amidst such an Universal Hurricane must be Solely Attributed to our Tutelar God Neptune, who with a Guard of winged Coursers so strongly Intrenches us,</hi> &amp;c. and you speak with assurance, that <hi>no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasion can be so sudden upon us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>but we shall get ready our whole Fleet, bring some Forces from</hi> Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>and prepare our own Millitia if there shall be occasion for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where you are so far from relying upon the <hi>Naval Strength,</hi> that you confess a necessity of <hi>preparing</hi> a <hi>Militia;</hi> and suppose it fit to have them supported by <hi>Regular Forces</hi> from <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in case all <hi>three</hi> Nations be Invaded at once, your Scheme of defence fails: And they who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand more of the Sea than you can pretend to, will tell you, that for near <hi>two third Parts</hi> of the year, with <hi>South</hi> or <hi>South-West</hi> Winds, the <hi>French</hi> may come upon us or <hi>Ireland,</hi> when our Fleet can't Stirr out to defend us; that in a few Hours time they may Tide it out of <hi>Fort-Lewis, Brest</hi> and <hi>Roch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and may come into their own open Bays; that from <hi>Stoaks</hi>-Bay they may be able to destroy our Fleet at <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> tho' we have a good Garison there, much more if there be not; and that at the very time when the Earl of <hi>Oreford</hi> obtained so Glorious a Victory, there were great odds against the probability that his Invicible Courage, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, and Diligence, should have carried out our Fleet at that time; and after all 'twas chance or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Providence, which united the Squadrons:
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:185067:34"/>This was much more <hi>Miraculous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Hist. p.</hi> 39.</note> than that <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rals</hi> should <hi>declare against the Fleet;</hi> when those <hi>Wing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Coursers</hi> have been insisted on as our only <hi>Guard.</hi> Besides, how sure soever that <hi>Guard</hi> be, how many <hi>Admirals</hi> would, like the Earl of <hi>Oreford,</hi> have run a greater risk at home than from the Enemy, in ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turing to preserve our Fleet and save the Nation, to the disappointment of the Intelligencers from hence, and hazard of an Impeachment, from men powerful to Accuse?</p>
            <p>Upon Cooler Thoughts, you have found out an other <hi>Guard</hi> besides the <hi>Fleet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Argument. p. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> which is a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> Reduced to 60000, a <hi>third Part</hi> of which should <hi>be kept by turns in constant Exercice:</hi> Into these, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to your Notion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Discipline, you admit Servants;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ib.</hi> Why may not a Man be listed till Discharged by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</note> but unluckily put the Officers upon a necessity of having raw Men, as often as Masters and Servants part. This Scheme you are so fond of, that you Dress it up in a particular Treatise, in which <hi>J. T.</hi> who is proud to own it, expatiates upon the <hi>Roman Story,</hi> and upon his Abilities to Write an History, which shall equal any of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and by which he should think to <hi>Dishonour</hi> some Men <hi>more, by silencing their Names, than by relating their Actions,</hi> which he counts <hi>Infamous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho' the <hi>Argument</hi> was his Copy for the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">vid. Sup. <hi>Militia Reform'd</hi> p. 18. <hi>p.</hi> 64.</note> his first Proposition is a Departure from it; confining the <hi>Militia</hi> to the <hi>Free-Men</hi> only: I need not run through all the absurdities of his Scheme; since he owns <hi>that all is irrecoverably</hi> lost, if <hi>you only oppose the Enemy with undisciplin'd multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:185067:35"/>
            <p>'Till therefore he shew it probable, That the Freemen will leave their Families and Professions, to follow the Exercice of Arms, and if they do, shall be expert Soldiers, before an Enemy can Land and march up to 'em; his <hi>Militia</hi> may be respit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, till he flourish an <hi>Archon</hi> at the Head of his <hi>Ʋtopia;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Life of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> p. <hi>122.</hi>
               </note> then he may divide to every one his share, according to the most <hi>perfect Form</hi> of a <hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,</hi> that <hi>ever was delineated</hi> by any Pen, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting Mr. <hi>Harrington</hi>'s own Description of the <hi>Jewish Commonwealth,</hi> or the more <hi>Ancient</hi> one, by the Inspired Writer <hi>Moses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But surely the Men of Property, who are so fond of the Complements he makes 'em, to draw 'em from their Trades and Families, do not consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that he deals with 'em, as you <hi>Gentlemen</hi> do with King <hi>William,</hi> and not only the last Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but even this, whom you apply to with all your Arts of sweetning, yet tell 'em in effect, that they destroy the Constitution. Some of your fine Flourishes to his <hi>Majesty,</hi> have been sufficiently Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd, by me and others; but who would have thought, that after you had said, <q>The whole Body of the People,<note place="margin">Letter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Guards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> in two Parliaments, have given sanction to the juster Opinion, and (with a true <hi>Roman</hi> Resolution, worthy their Illustrious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors, worthy the noblest, the manliest, the best Cause in the World, the Cause of Liberty) have declared, That they have Courage, Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, and Wisdom enough to defend themselves, and that they want no Keepers;</q> you should al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most in-the same breath, charge this very Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, with allowing the King <hi>near double as many Forces as are necessary?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Letter,</hi> p. 7.</note> and this without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sideration
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:185067:35"/>of the 12000 Men, which they would have kept up in <hi>Ireland,</hi> who, according to you, can be here whenever the King pleases; besides the 5000 in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and almost 6000 in <hi>Holland,</hi> which, as you reckon in all, amount to 33000 Men,<note place="margin">Letter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners p. 7.</note> and, as if they were all in <hi>England,</hi> call 'em <hi>a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and dreadful Force, and such an one as our Apostate Whigs, in any Reign, wherein they were not in the Ministry, would have thought sufficient to have Enslaved the Nation:</hi> but this very Parliament which you flatter, it seems has not made such provision against this dreadful Force as you, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>the Ministry,</hi> think sufficient to enslave the Nation.</p>
            <p>Besides, you should remember,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>History,</hi> p. 25.</note> That your Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry owns, that the last Parliament, which shares in your soothing Rhetorick, voted 350000 l. for <hi>Guards and Garrisons;</hi> you may know, that they computed this to be sufficient Maintenance for a year then to come, for some thousands more than this Parliament have voted; and that Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion was made accordingly, by an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Your Opinion of this, and all other <hi>Parliaments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>History,</hi> p. 20.</note> that have not judged by your Rules, appears by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Instances, especially by your Maxim, That the <hi>consent of Parliament</hi> would not make <hi>a standing Army</hi> (which in your lowest and latest acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is any Force more than is <hi>necessary</hi>) <hi>less dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But since, as I have shewn, Parliaments have generally trusted their Kings with regular Forces, or power to raise and keep them up, for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Kingdom (though indeed, when they
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:185067:36"/>had reason to be jealous of their Kings, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed some Great Men of their Choice, to have some share in the Trust) but according to you, all who urge the necessity of more than a good <hi>Fleet,</hi> and an un disciplined <hi>Militia,</hi> are Conspirators a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst their <hi>Country;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Argument, <hi>p. 17.</hi> The Conspirators say, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Can it be thought, that most of the <hi>Members</hi> of this and the last <hi>Parliament,</hi> where you may use that <hi>unbounded Liberty,</hi> which you labour for, are not charged with a <hi>Conspiracy</hi> or <hi>Apostacy,</hi> while the <hi>late,</hi> or <hi>non-Associators</hi> are the most <hi>sturdy Patriots?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But others will think, that they may with a juster freedom say, the Men who attempted, during the last Parliament, not only to have the <hi>Regular Forces</hi> disbanded, but the <hi>Militia,</hi> for a Project, which would require a Year at least for bringing to any head, were for inciting an Invasion; and however, according even to <hi>J. T.</hi> they could not be for the support of this Government; for he confesses, That <q>
                  <hi>all Countries must have some Force to defend them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Molitia Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,</hi> p. 16.</note>
                  <hi>against Foreign Invasions and Domestick Tumults;</hi> for as it was their own good and Security which occasioned men first to quit the state of Nature, and to associate themselves into Governments, so the <hi>raising and regulation of their Forces</hi> must be directed and and accommodated to the same ends.<note place="margin">What's the reason hee'd have this so defenceless. <hi>p. 17.</hi>
                  </note> An Island (says he) is best scituated for preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, as having need of little other Force, either to infest foreign Coasts, or to protect its own, besides a numerous Fleet, which it can never want. But if it be likewise a <hi>Government for encrease,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> This in substance in <hi>Harring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s Ocea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</note>
                  <hi>such as ours,</hi> its Scituation naturally leading it to Trade, and planting of Colonies; and if it has the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Ambition of holding the Ballance steddy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:185067:36"/>other Governments, of succouring the Distress'd, and grudging Liberty to none, <hi>[them it must be always provided with a considerable Land Force.]</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This, <hi>Gentlemen!</hi> is one of the Books,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>History,</hi> p. 2.</note> which if you don't all value your selves upon, is stampt with your particular Approbation: But since 'tis own'd, that <hi>a considerable Land Force is necessary for</hi> England; <hi>that all must be irrecoverably lost, if there be</hi> none but <hi>undisciplin'd Multitudes</hi> to oppose the <hi>Enemy;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Militia Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd,</hi> p. 73.</note> And 'tis not pretended, that the present <hi>Militia</hi> is yet suf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficiently Disciplin'd, or that your Project, if esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish'd, could soon be reduced to Practice and Order; and yet you would have the whole Army Disband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, having in your assuming way <hi>demonstrated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the possibility of a Reply,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Letter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners.</note>
               <hi>that small numbers of Men may and have destroyed the Liberties of Potent Nations;</hi> what can Men think of your <hi>Demonstrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> but that 'tis as much for the preservation of the Government, as charitable to the Soldiers, for whom, as you publickly insult, you have <hi>taken care, least they should be knock'd on the Head:</hi> But can any Man, who loves <hi>the Liberties of</hi> England join with them, who either would Sacrifice 'em to an <hi>Abdicated</hi> or <hi>Foreign Power,</hi> or to a meer <hi>Chimera,</hi> that most per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>form of a Commonwealth,</hi> which Mr. <hi>J. T.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends? not being aware of the danger of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passing</hi> and <hi>imagining</hi> the Subversion of the <hi>Monarchy:</hi> To Men of such designs, I will own there's more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from King <hi>William</hi> and his <hi>Protestant Successor,</hi> than from the <hi>late King,</hi> or <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Wales,</hi> tho' back'd by the Power of <hi>France,</hi> and that tho' <hi>Spain</hi> should be in <hi>French</hi> Hands.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:185067:37"/>
            <p>But would not the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> and other the <hi>Proprietors</hi> of <hi>England</hi> be very Wise, should they, or any number of 'em, be led by <hi>J. T.</hi> or the most Eloquent of you all, to struggle for his excellent <hi>form of a Commonwealth,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he has so fully open'd his Scene, and explain'd himself for the old <hi>levelling Agrarian,</hi> according to which, property must be put in <hi>Hotch-porch,</hi> and he, who has an unweildy share of Land within <hi>J. T</hi>'s <hi>Government,</hi> must submit to have it sliced and pared away, 'till 'tis but enough to furnish out the Owner and his Sons for the Wars.</p>
            <p>After all, how Ambitious soever he may be, of being thought an Eminent Promoter of that Model; they, who believe him in earnest, while they have good thoughts of his Sincerity, must undervalue his Understanding, to think he could impose upon himself, in the expectation of seeing it establish'd here: however, any thing that tends to the unsetling this Government, makes way for the Interest of the <hi>late King,</hi> or of that Religion which <hi>J. T.</hi> takes no small pains to disown.</p>
            <p>Tho' he undertake for the sense of <hi>all good Men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Life of</hi> Milton. <hi>History,</hi> p. 46.</note> as if 'twere against a Comprehension, least the <hi>Socinians</hi> should be crush'd; and you, for a <hi>considerable part of the Nation,</hi> that they <hi>will lye upon the Wheels with all their Weight,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less <hi>this Army,</hi> that is as the Words, and your whole drift imply, every Regiment, Troop and Company in it, be Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sbanded; the Judgment of this <hi>Parliament,</hi> as well as the <hi>last,</hi> and I may add of <hi>Parliaments</hi> in every Age of the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> cannot but be of greater Authority, than your hasty Opinions, with</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>(GENTLEMEM)</salute>
               <signed>Your's to Command upon the like Occasion.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>